<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-03-22T21:11:24-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Thousands</title><subtitle>Alicia No blogs about culture + stuff.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">HISTORY GLOWS RED</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/22/history-glows-red.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="HISTORY GLOWS RED" /><published>2020-03-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/03/22/history-glows-red</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/22/history-glows-red.html">&lt;p&gt;For those of us who are the mutts of humanity - born into a people but not fully the “real version”, not sophisticated blends of endorsed European stock, but the descendents of survivors that weren’t necessarily winners (although maybe winning is surviving), a complete history is not often our birthright. Whether your ancestors were the colonized or the enslaved or crossing borders they were not meant to, your history is probably missing from books. It probably lives in stories - wisps of hearsay passed down from someone who happened to be in the room when an older relative was telling stories, prejudices about the speaker twisting the weak points and layers of embellishment fossilizing to fill the space of things forgotten. And where are the facts? In some dusty old tome; perhaps missing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trying to piece together the history of artist Curtis Talwst Santiago likewise requires a little bit of effort. He has a Wikipedia page describing him as a Toronto-based dance-rock musician from Edmonton, Alberta, but to find his exact birth year (1979) one needs to click through several gallery page exhibition blurbs to find an extra-verbose CV. Other features highlight different aspects of his prolific career, such as his dioramas or video work, but in an attempt to maintain focus, ignore one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first encountered Curtis Talwst Santiago’s work when I popped into the Drawing Center in SoHo in early 2020 and saw the first few rooms of the gallery transformed into the multimedia installation &lt;em&gt;Can’t I Alter&lt;/em&gt;. With this collection of mixed media drawings and sculpture, Santiago brings viewers along with him on a journey through a world fed with personal experience, imagination and research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a stark childhood memory of his first encounter with J’Ouvert, a Trinidadi festival commemorating the first time formerly enslaved people could celebrate Carnival and a recent quest into the origins of a 16th century Flemish painting depicting an African Knight of the Order or Santiago, the artist birthed Sir Dingolay. Serving as both the show’s hero and the artist’s alter ego, Dingolay is one of the threads that ties together Can’t I Alter’s disparate elemements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately upon entering the viewer encounters a Sir Dingolay’s life-size beaded armor, (a reference to the mental ‘armor’ the artist needs traveling the world as a person on color), which feels at once solemn, joyful and imposing. Nestled inside &lt;em&gt;J’Ouvert Knight&lt;/em&gt;, (the only diorama in this collection) our hero appears in prescious miniature. “As with many such objects, this container was likely commissioned as a personal devotional object for a wealthy patron,” the catologue states. Sir Dingolay also makes an appearance in several of the medium-large (3 foot square) drawings on canvas that form the bread and butter of the exhibit, such as &lt;em&gt;Candy Flipping (Boogoo Pouring the Spell in Sir Dingolay’s Ear)&lt;/em&gt; or as a glowing silhouette in &lt;em&gt;The Four of them Made a Promise&lt;/em&gt;. If Sir Dingolay stands in for Curtis Talwst Santiago are these otherwordly traces based on the artist’s true history?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pair of spray-paint drawings on embossed tin tiles &lt;em&gt;She Knight&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;He Knight&lt;/em&gt;, further elaborate on the knight’s mythology. I feel these incarnations give the knight some gravitas; now that he has a companion he feels more like a person and less like a manic force tilting at windmills. Depicting both male and female knights on equal scale solidly refutes the antiquated misconception that the empowerment of men of color might depend on the disempowerment of women of color. In a music video playing in the central room Curtis Talwst Santiago finally dons the beaded armor and transforms into Sir Dirgolay. Surrounded by ruins with red pigment brightening his face, he dances the night away to his father’s favorite song (a Calypso tune by the Mighty Sparrow). In this way it all cascades down into the present, all brimming with blood and life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another motif is “red face”. Red clay face paint is a central part of of the J’ouvert festival, and by using reddish spraypaint to turn the faces of various ‘untitled ancestors’ and mythical creatures, the artist creates an interconnected mystique for these beings to which he pays homage. 
Other times spraypaint just represents a diffuse light, as in &lt;em&gt;A luz (the light)&lt;/em&gt;, bathing the entire drawing of a robed figure in an archway in a fuzzy glow. In &lt;em&gt;A morte do cavaleiro prateado (The Death of the Silver Knight&lt;/em&gt;, spraypaint illiminates the face of the J’Ouvert Knight and the nocturnal city in the distance, but neither the plants and trees of the foreground nor the face of the dying companion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Santiago incorporates real light in only one scupture – a giant nose the size of a motorcycle engine made of golden translucent glass, called &lt;em&gt;Warahoon&lt;/em&gt;. Tucked away behind a replica of a real stone arch that the artist lived near during his time in Bresca, Italy, the nose glows mysteriously from its place on a fluted columnar pedestal. Closer inspection reveals ths sculpture to be a bit tongue-in-cheek. “In leiu of the bust to which this nose belongs, the curators have chosen to display only the nose – the other side of the history so often seen in museums,” reads the exihibion catalogue. Iconoclasts seeking to deface statues of deceased individuals (e.g. grave robbers) in Anciant Egypt (Kemet) often broke off statues’ noses, leaving contemporary viewers with a slew of noseless (or worse, poorly restored Caucasian-nosed) statues. With this nose the artist pays a tribute to all the noses lost to history, and all the stories lost with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I may not be Triniadi, and the blanks I have to fill in may look different from Santiago’s, but seeing this body of work gave me a sense of hope that’s hard to describe. It felt as if this series of attempts to evoke something elusive yet vital. That even if you can’t ever get to a full picture, it’s worth chasing after the blanks in the historical record. Its worth looking for your ancestors. It’s possible to create your own mythology. Imagining in the blanks doesn’t necessarily make your mythology less real.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">For those of us who are the mutts of humanity - born into a people but not fully the “real version”, not sophisticated blends of endorsed European stock, but the descendents of survivors that weren’t necessarily winners (although maybe winning is surviving), a complete history is not often our birthright. Whether your ancestors were the colonized or the enslaved or crossing borders they were not meant to, your history is probably missing from books. It probably lives in stories - wisps of hearsay passed down from someone who happened to be in the room when an older relative was telling stories, prejudices about the speaker twisting the weak points and layers of embellishment fossilizing to fill the space of things forgotten. And where are the facts? In some dusty old tome; perhaps missing.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PINES</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/11/pines.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PINES" /><published>2020-03-11T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/03/11/pines</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/11/pines.html">&lt;p&gt;A FEW DAYS after the first cases of COVID-19 hit the streets of New York City, I was not yet cowering in my apartment. I found myself at Webster Hall in the East Village, defiantly packed into a crowd of fans waiting to see two members of the 070 collective. The opener 070 Phi rapped about his “last year of being broke, family, and hustling. Then 070 Shake was just pure energy, a being from something like our collective imagination of the future come back to tell us some things about her life. The floor was sticky, a silver blow-up doll and an inflatable boat surfed the crowd, and a lot of 20 year olds from New Jersey obliviously elbowed me again and again. It was mostly worth the abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toward the end of the set she and the audience all burst out “THE PINES, THE PINES, WHERE WHERE THE SUN DON’T EVER SHINE?” and at that moment the song I’ve been casually humming along to comes into a new focus. Although the mic setup is still supplying her signature autotune, now that its live the many layers of production (a department where it IMO G. O. O. D. music was a little too heavy-handed) fall away, exposing more  I get this nerdy “aha” moment where I’m like, whoa its that Lead Belly song!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1993 Nirvana reinterpreted “Where Did You Sleep Last Night” and recorded it as part of their famed MTV Unplugged set. It was creepy. When I discovered Nirvana like a decade later, scouring my parents’ house for literally anything to drown out the sounds of middle school, it was creepy, hearing this man shrieking at this young woman, incensed she would lie to him about where she slept last night. It chilled me to hear this hushed-up reality of domestic male rage being admitted in this way. I think I assumed it was about infidelity, and maybe for Cobain it was. Like a lot of Nirvana lyrics it felt like a riddle, a mystery you could flip different ways, and I held tight to it as something I might understand later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually I did an internet search and found out the song was actually a lot older. In 1941 and 1952 Bill Monroe (called the “Father of Bluegrass”) recorded versions of a southern Appalachian folk song sometimes also called “The Longest Train” under the name “In the Pines.” The lyrics in this version describe a train that took three hours to pass and allude to a “little girl” the narrator is mourning without being too specific. In 1944 and 1948 Huddie Ledbetter (stage name: Lead Belly) interpreted the folk song in a more violent an haunting way. Here the narrator seems to be a Black woman mourning the loss of her husband and daughter, decapitated by a moving train and dumped in a pine forest where she cannot find them. Many other versions of this song have been recorded, in music genres from Cajun zydeco to British pop, but the Lead Belly version is the version Kurt Cobain learned from fellow 1990’s Seattle musician Mark Lanegan, and based on the grungy heavy-distortion baseline that opens 070 Shake’s “The Pines”, I’m pretty sure this is the version being referenced here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even given this ultimate chameleon of a song, all this is backstory is just a footnote for futurist 070 Shake. “The Pines” is a completely different song. She re-uses the chorus, but the verse is more free-form, more rap. It’s about betrayal, bitterness and probably infidelity, but I don’t get domestic violence vibes here. Instead of a train beheading the villain (in some versions of “In the Pines”, this is how a rapist is killed after his victim escapes into a pine forest), Shake just says “I gotta go/Headed home/To a different timezone.” In the music video, Shake dials up the violence, but drops the romantic themes as she depicts a physical fight that takes place woods between herself and one of her male friends. After the fight which gets ugly to the point of spitting, the video ends with the whole group hanging out in their New Jersey neighborhood like nothing’s wrong. Maybe the fight was just about toughening one another up, or finding an outlet for external rage?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of ways places to put you rage, it’s getting borderline in here. Despite clouds of THC vapor, no one is chill. Shake is grandstanding about loving our neighbors while a guy yells at his date for putting her fingers in his nose. We bounce and cheer to banger after banger, each one it’s own groovy cyborgian musical moment. A beer-soaked dude soaked slams into me and my inner punk launches itself into the moshing abyss. My anxiety and angst rolls off in blissful waves, til I make eye contact with a woman whose looking kinda upset. Next time my feet touch down I allow them to stick in the sugary residue of a spilled drink. Shake hits a crescendo with “Under the Moon” and then plays us out with “Violent Crimes,” the closing track on Kanye’s 2018 album “Ye” that first launched Shake and the 070 collective into the national spotlight. It’s the future, it’s the past, it’s the slow-moving semi-apocalyptic now. Keep slaying NJ. Work on your physical self-awareness if you can.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A FEW DAYS after the first cases of COVID-19 hit the streets of New York City, I was not yet cowering in my apartment. I found myself at Webster Hall in the East Village, defiantly packed into a crowd of fans waiting to see two members of the 070 collective. The opener 070 Phi rapped about his “last year of being broke, family, and hustling. Then 070 Shake was just pure energy, a being from something like our collective imagination of the future come back to tell us some things about her life. The floor was sticky, a silver blow-up doll and an inflatable boat surfed the crowd, and a lot of 20 year olds from New Jersey obliviously elbowed me again and again. It was mostly worth the abuse.</summary></entry></feed>