<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-05-31T18:21:19-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">M.O.T.</title><subtitle>a blog, a &quot;mother-of-thousands&quot; of things.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">EVERYTHING IS AN ECHO OF ITSELF</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/05/14/labyrinths.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EVERYTHING IS AN ECHO OF ITSELF" /><published>2020-05-14T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/05/14/labyrinths</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/05/14/labyrinths.html">&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/burlington-all-saints-comm-labyrinth.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A photo taken from the entrance of a walking labyrinth laid out in the middle of a slightly patchy field of grass.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The labyrinth at All Saints Community Labyrinth follows the Chartes pattern.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    if (document.getElementById(&quot;&quot;)) {
      var images = document.getElementById(&quot;&quot;).getElementsByTagName(&quot;img&quot;);
      var img;
      if (images &amp;&amp; images.length &gt; 0) {
        img = images[0];
        if (img &amp;&amp; img.src) {
          var imgSrc = img.src;
          var loader = new window.Image();
          loader.src = '';
          loader.onload = function () {
            var imageComponent = document.getElementById(&quot;&quot;);
            imageComponent.classList.add(&quot;ImageComponent--loaded&quot;)
          }
          loader.src = imgSrc;
        }
      }
    } else {
      console.log(&quot;Warning: ImageComponent registered without img_key. Loading behavior will be broken.&quot;);
    }
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;entering&quot;&gt;Entering&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I had no experience of labyrinths before encountering one on an afternoon walk. In the corner of a church lawn downtown, a brick-framed-grass path coiled around a thick oak. Not having anything else to do, I considered following it. I didn’t know if it’d feel long or short or if I’d be lost but I asked my body if it was okay with either outcome and it said yes. As a result I spent 15 continuous minutes tracing an undulating circle, while townspeople hustled along the street grid, purposefully traveling from place to place. To be honest, I felt a bit vulnerable, on display. Who was I to flaunt my curvy path among those who only went straight?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These humans will make metaphors out of anything. We also walk around a lot, getting lost. To me this feels like the human condition. Intentionally disorienting paths have popped up on nearly every continent on the planet. There are two main types: unicursal (non-branching) and multicursal (having several branches and usually one solution). Multicursal labyrinths commonly exist for recreational or defensive purposes — think hedge mazes, or the labyrinth where David Bowie hides Sarah’s baby brother in the Jim Henson film Labyrinth (1986). Unicursal labyrinths are more about introspection. I’ve decided to call these ones with unicursal paths “labyrinths” and multicursal paths “mazes”. This contradicts the word labyrinth’s Greek roots — in the myth, King Minos has a beloved yet terribly destructive pet called the Minotaur (anyone else wonder if this was just a euphemism for some royal anger management issues?), so he commissions Daedalus to contain it in an inescapable underground maze. This mostly works fairly well, keeping the people of Crete safe from attack so long as Minos continues to feed it with yearly sacrifices. Historians believe that the tale of the angry mythological beast trapped deep in the earth was invented to explain the earthquakes that regularly plagued Crete for a reason no one understood. Something must have been lost in translation as two millennia past, because these non-branching floor installations I’m talking about today are all called “labyrinths”. So I suppose “labyrinth” still is the word to use.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“If you liked that labyrinth, I have another one for you,” Rhoen said, and our whole house piled into the car the next morning, parking at an empty parking lot next to a scrubby garden. On one side of the garden was a freshly plowed farm and a little marsh; a building that must have been the church was on the other. A sign with a lengthy poem invited all who read it to enter. Crossing a small bridge, I strode straight into the labyrinth. Rhoen followed after spending time addressing the plaques and stone statues. Aneken sat on a bench looking around. They started when they were ready.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/labyrinth-lauren-artress.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A silver haired woman with glasses sits in an arm chair, gesturing toward a circular labyrinth diagram.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Lauren Artress, founder of the Labyrinth Movement, holds a diagram of the floor pattern Chartres Cathedral.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    if (document.getElementById(&quot;&quot;)) {
      var images = document.getElementById(&quot;&quot;).getElementsByTagName(&quot;img&quot;);
      var img;
      if (images &amp;&amp; images.length &gt; 0) {
        img = images[0];
        if (img &amp;&amp; img.src) {
          var imgSrc = img.src;
          var loader = new window.Image();
          loader.src = '';
          loader.onload = function () {
            var imageComponent = document.getElementById(&quot;&quot;);
            imageComponent.classList.add(&quot;ImageComponent--loaded&quot;)
          }
          loader.src = imgSrc;
        }
      }
    } else {
      console.log(&quot;Warning: ImageComponent registered without img_key. Loading behavior will be broken.&quot;);
    }
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;arriving&quot;&gt;Arriving&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I arrive at the center. I am consciously not in a rush. Standing tall, I am learning to focus on me and not on those people in their grid. I greet the oak by walking around it once, giving it enough attention that I hope it won’t feel disrespected. I don’t say hello or goodbye.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lauren Artress started the Labyrinth Movement after a 1991 encounter with Jean Houston (founder of the Human Potential Movement) inspired her to travel to France to walk a labyrinth at the Cathédrale Notre-Dame de Chartres.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; Artress and her companions pushed aside the chairs and walked the eleven course, non-branching Medieval labyrinth built into the nave floor tiles for the first time in 250 years. When she returned home to Grace Cathedral in San Francisco, where she is a priest, she copied the design from Chartres onto a canvas floor tapestry and began to introduce others to the labyrinth, with great success.&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; Given the pervasive but uninformed interest in meditation and “Eastern philosophy” that was popular at the time, it is easy to see why. Labyrinths are simple to make, simple to use, and feel culturally familiar to people from European backgrounds. First working with various personal contacts in the United States and with the International Transpersonal Association in Europe, and eventually creating a non-profit called Veriditas, Artress made it her mission to bring labyrinths to cathedrals, public parks, healthcare facilities, prisons, backyards and spas in many countries.&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; After decades of progress, the organization’s goal has evolved to focus on how to best harness the Labyrinth Experience to facilitate “the transformation of the human spirit”.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I tell myself not to feel underwhelmed at the puddle of gravel that awaits me. I remember when I turned twelve and felt cheated when I realized my birthday did not grant me any more abilities or privileges and, crying, I asked my mother why. I felt even sadder when she told me there wasn’t an answer. Rhoen and then Aneken arrive too and I think about all the highschool kids forced to have quarantine graduations. How important is a threshold to mark the passage of time? I notice that around the large puddle of gray gravel there are smaller rays of red gravel and I put out my arms and start to spin, til red merges with gray and farm merges with road and mirror neurons turn three human bodies into oversized imitations of the year’s last snow flurries swirling in space. For a moment, we’re all here. Eventually we won’t be.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/labyrinth-cretan-coin.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Black and white scanned images of two silver coins bearing the Greek letters K N O.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Silver coins from second century Crete embossed with the labyrinth illustrate the Classical 7-course pattern.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    if (document.getElementById(&quot;&quot;)) {
      var images = document.getElementById(&quot;&quot;).getElementsByTagName(&quot;img&quot;);
      var img;
      if (images &amp;&amp; images.length &gt; 0) {
        img = images[0];
        if (img &amp;&amp; img.src) {
          var imgSrc = img.src;
          var loader = new window.Image();
          loader.src = '';
          loader.onload = function () {
            var imageComponent = document.getElementById(&quot;&quot;);
            imageComponent.classList.add(&quot;ImageComponent--loaded&quot;)
          }
          loader.src = imgSrc;
        }
      }
    } else {
      console.log(&quot;Warning: ImageComponent registered without img_key. Loading behavior will be broken.&quot;);
    }
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;leaving&quot;&gt;Leaving&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now all that’s left is to leave the way you came. Exiting the center, I feel like a pro. The path has already proven itself so there’s no need for a leap of faith. What’s left is just to put one foot in front of the other. All that’s left is just to believe that I can and I will.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the time of their construction, most gothic cathedrals had labyrinths.&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; Their exact function is not precisely known, but clues survive: a description of French clerics using a floor labyrinth in an Easter ceremony; illustrations of pilgrims traversing the labyrinth on their knees; the late 18th century French word for cathedral labyrinths being “chemin de Jerusalem” – literally ‘path to Jerusalem’, which Christians view as the Holy Land.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; Most of these cathedral labyrinths were eventually deemed ‘distracting’ and removed. This makes Chartres an outlier. Despite the labyrinth movement’s adoption by plenty of fringey Christians, mainstream ones dismiss the movement as a New Age-y fad at best, vaguely pagan at worst. And I suppose it is both of these things. Now that I have been initiated, it seems Iabyrinths are everywhere, although not dramatically advertised. And although the four-quadrant unicursal Chartres design was the one that initially inspired Artress, 20th century labyrinths might also opt for the more unified “Classical” design embossed on Cretan coins from 430 BCE,&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; invent their own design, or choose a unicursal maze pattern from Celtic, Hindu or Native American lore. There are no hard and fast rules. Cultural context here is treated as secondary, almost decorative. The primary thing is the walking.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rhoen threatens to break the walls on the way back, so we settle on a run. Bouncing around the labyrinths’ four quadrants I surge ahead of the others, only to fall behind when the path switchbacks in the opposite direction. My lungs burn, I wonder if I’ll trip at the next turn, or the next. I think it’s over sooner than it is, accidentally puncturing the wall of one of the final bends before the neck of the exit. On leaving I circle the exterior, noting commemorative bricks, and reflecting on what just happened. There’s a sundial feature made by a man Rhoen knows from childhood. He exits, and then Aneken, in their own time. We don’t say much of anything. We’ve been on the same path but there were three separate journeys.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The labyrinth at All Saints Community Labyrinth follows the Chartes pattern.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">HISTORY GLOWS RED</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/22/talwst-cant-i-alter.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="HISTORY GLOWS RED" /><published>2020-03-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/03/22/talwst-cant-i-alter</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/22/talwst-cant-i-alter.html">&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent&quot; id=&quot;talwst__knight-diorama&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://format-com-cld-res.cloudinary.com/image/private/s--dWZ_0RMF--/c_limit,g_center,h_65535,w_1200/fl_keep_iptc.progressive,q_95/v1/e42850d2e43af68f9c786a5841b3554e/CSA-34a-SC.jpg?1200&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Artist as Knight (self portrait). Curtis Talwst Santiago. 2018&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    if (document.getElementById(&quot;talwst__knight-diorama&quot;)) {
      var images = document.getElementById(&quot;talwst__knight-diorama&quot;).getElementsByTagName(&quot;img&quot;);
      var img;
      if (images &amp;&amp; images.length &gt; 0) {
        img = images[0];
        if (img &amp;&amp; img.src) {
          var imgSrc = img.src;
          var loader = new window.Image();
          loader.src = '';
          loader.onload = function () {
            var imageComponent = document.getElementById(&quot;talwst__knight-diorama&quot;);
            imageComponent.classList.add(&quot;ImageComponent--loaded&quot;)
          }
          loader.src = imgSrc;
        }
      }
    } else {
      console.log(&quot;Warning: ImageComponent registered without img_key. Loading behavior will be broken.&quot;);
    }
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to describe how experiencing the collection of work by Curtis Talwst Santiago on view at the Drawing Center made me feel. So I’ll settle for describing what I saw in this show entitled “Can’t I Alter”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;Post__spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon entering, visitors first encounter a life-sized, beaded suit of armor, nestled in an arch of crumbling plaster supported by iron construction scaffolding. The scenery evokes ancient ruins and the streets of New York, which fits. The work here is the result of a journey that has taken Santiago all over the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent&quot; id=&quot;talwst__install-1&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://format-com-cld-res.cloudinary.com/image/private/s--YtKPvDxr--/c_limit,g_center,h_65535,w_2500/fl_keep_iptc.progressive,q_95/IMG_2004_paj12w.jpg?2500&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Installation view at the Drawing Center in February of 2020.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    if (document.getElementById(&quot;talwst__install-1&quot;)) {
      var images = document.getElementById(&quot;talwst__install-1&quot;).getElementsByTagName(&quot;img&quot;);
      var img;
      if (images &amp;&amp; images.length &gt; 0) {
        img = images[0];
        if (img &amp;&amp; img.src) {
          var imgSrc = img.src;
          var loader = new window.Image();
          loader.src = '';
          loader.onload = function () {
            var imageComponent = document.getElementById(&quot;talwst__install-1&quot;);
            imageComponent.classList.add(&quot;ImageComponent--loaded&quot;)
          }
          loader.src = imgSrc;
        }
      }
    } else {
      console.log(&quot;Warning: ImageComponent registered without img_key. Loading behavior will be broken.&quot;);
    }
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a stark childhood memory of his first encounter with &lt;em&gt;J’Ouvert&lt;/em&gt;, a Trinidadi festival commemorating the first time formerly enslaved people could celebrate Carnival, and a recent quest into the origins of a 16th century Flemish painting depicting an African Knight of the Order or Santiago, the artist birthed his character ‘Sir Dingolay’. Serving as both the show’s hero and the artist’s alter ego, Sir Dingolay’s presence helps to unite the fruits of the artist’s versatile talents. (In addition to being a thoughtful painter, and an inspired 3-D artist, Santiago is widely acclaimed for his miniature dioramas and has also had a successful career as a Toronto-based dance-rock musician. This might explain his fluency with so many media)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;Post__spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entrance to the show immediately introduces Sir Dingolay in  the form of  his rather festive suit of armor, a life-size garment woven from black, red, white and green beads and wire. Besides evoking the presence of our hero, the wearable sculpture also references the mental ‘armor’ the artist describes needing while traveling the world as a person on color. Nestled inside J’Ouvert Knight, (the only diorama in this collection) our hero appears again in precious miniature. “As with many such objects, this container was likely commissioned as a personal devotional object for a wealthy patron,” the catalogue states. Sir Dingolay also makes an appearance in several of the medium-large in (3 foot square) drawings on canvas that form the bread-and-butter of the exhibit, somewhat ambiguously in &lt;em&gt;Candy Flipping (Boogoo Pouring the Spell in Sir Dingolay’s Ear)&lt;/em&gt; or as a glowing silhouette in &lt;em&gt;The Four of them Made a Promise&lt;/em&gt;. If Sir Dingolay stands in for Curtis Talwst Santiago, are these otherworldly traces based on the artist’s true history?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent&quot; id=&quot;talwst__morte-do-cavaliero&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://format-com-cld-res.cloudinary.com/image/private/s--atUKTDMv--/c_limit,g_center,h_65535,w_1200/fl_keep_iptc.progressive,q_95/v1/e249373eab34260530f3d240a269f61a/CSA-9-PTG.jpg?1200&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&quot;A morte do cavaleiro prateado.&quot; Spraypaint, oil, charcoal, pastel, acrylic on canvas. 2018&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    if (document.getElementById(&quot;talwst__morte-do-cavaliero&quot;)) {
      var images = document.getElementById(&quot;talwst__morte-do-cavaliero&quot;).getElementsByTagName(&quot;img&quot;);
      var img;
      if (images &amp;&amp; images.length &gt; 0) {
        img = images[0];
        if (img &amp;&amp; img.src) {
          var imgSrc = img.src;
          var loader = new window.Image();
          loader.src = '';
          loader.onload = function () {
            var imageComponent = document.getElementById(&quot;talwst__morte-do-cavaliero&quot;);
            imageComponent.classList.add(&quot;ImageComponent--loaded&quot;)
          }
          loader.src = imgSrc;
        }
      }
    } else {
      console.log(&quot;Warning: ImageComponent registered without img_key. Loading behavior will be broken.&quot;);
    }
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent&quot; id=&quot;talwst__ancestral-vision&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://format-com-cld-res.cloudinary.com/image/private/s--xejNTiIN--/c_limit,g_center,h_65535,w_1200/fl_keep_iptc.progressive,q_95/v1/60540d89c0012c97d3e5fe228282b82f/CSA-7-PTG.jpg?1200&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&quot;Red Face Ancestral Vision 1.&quot; Spraypaint, oil, charcoal, pastel, acrylic on canvas. 2018&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    if (document.getElementById(&quot;talwst__ancestral-vision&quot;)) {
      var images = document.getElementById(&quot;talwst__ancestral-vision&quot;).getElementsByTagName(&quot;img&quot;);
      var img;
      if (images &amp;&amp; images.length &gt; 0) {
        img = images[0];
        if (img &amp;&amp; img.src) {
          var imgSrc = img.src;
          var loader = new window.Image();
          loader.src = '';
          loader.onload = function () {
            var imageComponent = document.getElementById(&quot;talwst__ancestral-vision&quot;);
            imageComponent.classList.add(&quot;ImageComponent--loaded&quot;)
          }
          loader.src = imgSrc;
        }
      }
    } else {
      console.log(&quot;Warning: ImageComponent registered without img_key. Loading behavior will be broken.&quot;);
    }
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pair of spray-paint drawings on embossed tin tiles She Knight and He Knight, further elaborate on the knight’s mythology. These give the knight some more gravitas; now that he has a companion I start to imagine this avatar as having a life of his own, parallel but separate from the artist. Depicting both male and female knights on equal scale solidly refutes an antiquated belief that the struggle for empowerment men of color face might   require the disempowerment of women of color; in Santiago’s world both the He Knight, She Knight, and the artist himself are magnificent and build one another up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;Post__spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another motif is “red face”. Red clay face paint is a central part of of the J’ouvert festival, and by using reddish spray-paint to turn the faces of various ‘untitled ancestors’ and mythical creatures, the artist creates an interconnected mystique for these beings to which he pays homage. Other times spray-paint just represents a diffuse light, as in A luz (the light), bathing the entire drawing of a robed figure in an archway in a fuzzy glow. In &lt;em&gt;A morte do cavaleiro prateado (The Death of the Silver Knight)&lt;/em&gt;, spray-paint illuminates the face of the J’Ouvert Knight and the nocturnal city in the distance, but neither the plants and trees of the foreground nor the face of the dying companion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent&quot; id=&quot;talwst__promise&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://format-com-cld-res.cloudinary.com/image/private/s--96jRsjOb--/c_limit,g_center,h_65535,w_1200/fl_keep_iptc.progressive,q_95/v1/17bb9e11cf6b1ef5b5d7090a21b25d7a/CSA-10-PTG.jpg?1200&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&quot;The Four of Them Made a Promise.&quot; Spray paint, oil, charcoal, pastel, acrylic on canvas. 2018&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    if (document.getElementById(&quot;talwst__promise&quot;)) {
      var images = document.getElementById(&quot;talwst__promise&quot;).getElementsByTagName(&quot;img&quot;);
      var img;
      if (images &amp;&amp; images.length &gt; 0) {
        img = images[0];
        if (img &amp;&amp; img.src) {
          var imgSrc = img.src;
          var loader = new window.Image();
          loader.src = '';
          loader.onload = function () {
            var imageComponent = document.getElementById(&quot;talwst__promise&quot;);
            imageComponent.classList.add(&quot;ImageComponent--loaded&quot;)
          }
          loader.src = imgSrc;
        }
      }
    } else {
      console.log(&quot;Warning: ImageComponent registered without img_key. Loading behavior will be broken.&quot;);
    }
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent&quot; id=&quot;talwst__sir-dingolay&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://format-com-cld-res.cloudinary.com/image/private/s--7zYpIEB3--/c_limit,g_center,h_65535,w_1200/fl_keep_iptc.progressive,q_95/IMG_2020_qhrl27.jpg?1200&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&quot;Sir Dingolay&quot;. Video. 2020.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    if (document.getElementById(&quot;talwst__sir-dingolay&quot;)) {
      var images = document.getElementById(&quot;talwst__sir-dingolay&quot;).getElementsByTagName(&quot;img&quot;);
      var img;
      if (images &amp;&amp; images.length &gt; 0) {
        img = images[0];
        if (img &amp;&amp; img.src) {
          var imgSrc = img.src;
          var loader = new window.Image();
          loader.src = '';
          loader.onload = function () {
            var imageComponent = document.getElementById(&quot;talwst__sir-dingolay&quot;);
            imageComponent.classList.add(&quot;ImageComponent--loaded&quot;)
          }
          loader.src = imgSrc;
        }
      }
    } else {
      console.log(&quot;Warning: ImageComponent registered without img_key. Loading behavior will be broken.&quot;);
    }
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Santiago incorporates real light in only one sculpture – a giant nose the size of a motorcycle engine made of golden translucent glass, called &lt;em&gt;Warahoon&lt;/em&gt;. Tucked away behind a replica of a real stone arch that the artist lived near during his time in Bresca, Italy, the nose glows mysteriously from its place on a fluted columnar pedestal. Closer inspection reveals this sculpture to be a bit tongue-in-cheek. “In leiu of the bust to which this nose belongs, the curators have chosen to display only the nose – the other side of the history so often seen in museums,” reads the exhibition catalogue. Iconoclasts seeking to deface statues of deceased individuals (e.g. grave robbers) in Ancient Egypt (Kemet) often broke off statues’ noses, leaving contemporary viewers with a slew of noseless (or worse, poorly restored Caucasian-nosed) statues. With this nose the artist pays a tribute to all the noses lost to history, and all the stories lost with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;Post__spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/398961557&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;music video&lt;/a&gt; plays in the central room, adding a groovy, exciting soundtrack that grounds so many history-defying objects in the honest present. We see the artist finally don the beaded armor and transform into Sir Dingolay. Surrounded by ruins with red pigment brightening his face, he dances the night away to his father’s favorite song (a Calypso tune by the Mighty Sparrow). In this way it all cascades down into the present, all brimming with blood and life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent&quot; id=&quot;talwst__santiago-with-knight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/curtis-talwst-santiago-with-armor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The artist poses next to &quot;African Knight I&quot; (wire and beads, on steel armature, 2018).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    if (document.getElementById(&quot;talwst__santiago-with-knight&quot;)) {
      var images = document.getElementById(&quot;talwst__santiago-with-knight&quot;).getElementsByTagName(&quot;img&quot;);
      var img;
      if (images &amp;&amp; images.length &gt; 0) {
        img = images[0];
        if (img &amp;&amp; img.src) {
          var imgSrc = img.src;
          var loader = new window.Image();
          loader.src = '';
          loader.onload = function () {
            var imageComponent = document.getElementById(&quot;talwst__santiago-with-knight&quot;);
            imageComponent.classList.add(&quot;ImageComponent--loaded&quot;)
          }
          loader.src = imgSrc;
        }
      }
    } else {
      console.log(&quot;Warning: ImageComponent registered without img_key. Loading behavior will be broken.&quot;);
    }
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Experiencing this body of work gave me a sense of hope that’s hard to describe. Seeing the artist presenting a heavily realized vision of his personal history — not a history that was written for him by the institution, but a history he sought out and nurtured and imagined into reality — seemed to acknowledge a secret desire I’ve secretly always had for a “better” history. As one of the mutts of the post-colonial society we call the United States, my history always ran contrary to the versions I learned about in school. There are so many blanks, blanks that there will never be adequate records to fill. In “Can’t I Alter”, Santiago seems to argue that with some creativity, a person can take this on. That it’s worth looking for your ancestors, even if their forms come a bit fuzzy. It’s totally possible to create your own mythology. Who’s to say your mythology is less real.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Artist as Knight (self portrait). Curtis Talwst Santiago. 2018</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PINES</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/11/pines.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PINES" /><published>2020-03-11T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/03/11/pines</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/11/pines.html">&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/070-shake-pines.png&quot; alt=&quot;070 Shake lights a cigarette in front of a group of her friend after a fight. One young man is supported between two others.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The music video for 070 Shake's song &quot;Pines&quot; includes a gnarly fight scene.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    if (document.getElementById(&quot;&quot;)) {
      var images = document.getElementById(&quot;&quot;).getElementsByTagName(&quot;img&quot;);
      var img;
      if (images &amp;&amp; images.length &gt; 0) {
        img = images[0];
        if (img &amp;&amp; img.src) {
          var imgSrc = img.src;
          var loader = new window.Image();
          loader.src = '';
          loader.onload = function () {
            var imageComponent = document.getElementById(&quot;&quot;);
            imageComponent.classList.add(&quot;ImageComponent--loaded&quot;)
          }
          loader.src = imgSrc;
        }
      }
    } else {
      console.log(&quot;Warning: ImageComponent registered without img_key. Loading behavior will be broken.&quot;);
    }
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days after the first official cases of COVID-19 hit the streets of New York City, I am embarassed to admit I was not yet cowering in my apartment. Instead I was at Webster Hall, in a claustrophobic crowd of fans waiting to see two members of the 070 collective. The first act was 070 Phi, an oddly wise Gen Z-er with glasses and braids, serving up some good quality rap. Then 070 Shake came along to launched us into a new dimension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;Post__spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shake is an engrossing performer, just pure scrappy energy, like a tough being from our collective imagination of the future, come back for a single night to tell us some things about her life. The audience responded with enthusiasm. People screamed loudly on cue, a silver blow-up doll surfed the crod in an inflatable row boat. A lot of 20 year olds from New Jersey bought sugary alcoholic drinks which they spilled liberally while obliviously elbowing me again and again. Doing the math, it was mostly worth the abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;Post__spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toward the end of the set she and the audience all burst out “THE PINES, THE PINES, WHERE WHERE THE SUN DON’T EVER SHINE?” and at that moment the song I’ve been casually humming along to comes into a new focus. Although the mic setup still supplies her signature autotune, now that its live the many layers of production (in which the influence of G.O.O.D. music is dramatic to the point of being overbearing) fall away, exposing more  I get this nerdy “aha” moment where I’m like, whoa its that Lead Belly song!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;Post__spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1993 Nirvana reinterpreted “Where Did You Sleep Last Night” and recorded it as part of their famed MTV Unplugged set.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; It was creepy. When I discovered Nirvana like a decade later, scouring my parents’ house for literally anything to drown out the sounds of middle school, it was creepy, hearing this man shrieking at this young woman, incensed she would lie to him about where she slept last night. It chilled me to hear this hushed-up reality of domestic male rage being admitted in this way. I think I assumed it was about infidelity, and maybe for Cobain it was. Like a lot of Nirvana lyrics it felt like a riddle, a mystery you could flip different ways, and I held tight to it as something I might understand later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/07/Huddie_Ledbetter_%28Leadbelly%29_taken_by_Alan_Lomax.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A black and white photograph of Huddie Ledbetter wearing a plaid suit and holding an acoustic guitar&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;A photograph of Huddie &quot;Leadbelly&quot; Ledbetter, taken by Alan Lomax in the 1940's.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    if (document.getElementById(&quot;&quot;)) {
      var images = document.getElementById(&quot;&quot;).getElementsByTagName(&quot;img&quot;);
      var img;
      if (images &amp;&amp; images.length &gt; 0) {
        img = images[0];
        if (img &amp;&amp; img.src) {
          var imgSrc = img.src;
          var loader = new window.Image();
          loader.src = '';
          loader.onload = function () {
            var imageComponent = document.getElementById(&quot;&quot;);
            imageComponent.classList.add(&quot;ImageComponent--loaded&quot;)
          }
          loader.src = imgSrc;
        }
      }
    } else {
      console.log(&quot;Warning: ImageComponent registered without img_key. Loading behavior will be broken.&quot;);
    }
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://66.media.tumblr.com/92d772fe3f0c7bd23616093da6e91e04/tumblr_oa83w7bhYt1tyu4qdo1_400.gifv&quot; alt=&quot;Cobain passionately sings the chorus, seated at the mic with his eyes closed.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Kurt Cobain singing &quot;Where Did You Sleep Last Night&quot; with Nirvana at their  historic MTV Unplugged show.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    if (document.getElementById(&quot;&quot;)) {
      var images = document.getElementById(&quot;&quot;).getElementsByTagName(&quot;img&quot;);
      var img;
      if (images &amp;&amp; images.length &gt; 0) {
        img = images[0];
        if (img &amp;&amp; img.src) {
          var imgSrc = img.src;
          var loader = new window.Image();
          loader.src = '';
          loader.onload = function () {
            var imageComponent = document.getElementById(&quot;&quot;);
            imageComponent.classList.add(&quot;ImageComponent--loaded&quot;)
          }
          loader.src = imgSrc;
        }
      }
    } else {
      console.log(&quot;Warning: ImageComponent registered without img_key. Loading behavior will be broken.&quot;);
    }
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually I did an internet search and found out the song was actually a lot older. In 1941 and 1952 Bill Monroe (called the “Father of Bluegrass”)&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; recorded versions of a southern Appalachian folk song sometimes also called “The Longest Train” under the name “In the Pines.”&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; The lyrics in this version describe a train that took three hours to pass and allude to a “little girl” the narrator is mourning without being too specific. In 1944 and 1948 Huddie Ledbetter (stage name: Lead Belly) interpreted the folk song in a more violent an haunting way. Here the narrator seems to be a Black woman mourning the loss of her husband and daughter, decapitated by a moving train and dumped in a pine forest where she cannot find them. Many other versions of this song have been recorded, in music genres from Cajun zydeco to British pop, but the Lead Belly version is the version Kurt Cobain learned from fellow 1990’s Seattle musician Mark Lanegan, and based on the grungy heavy-distortion baseline that opens 070 Shake’s “The Pines”, I’m pretty sure this is the version being referenced here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;Post__spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even given this ultimate chameleon of a song, all this is backstory is just a footnote for futurist 070 Shake. “The Pines” is a completely different song. She re-uses the chorus, but the verse is more free-form, more rap. It’s about betrayal, bitterness and probably infidelity, but I don’t get domestic violence vibes here. Instead of a train beheading the villain (in some versions of “In the Pines”, this is how a rapist is killed after his victim escapes into a pine forest), Shake just says “I gotta go/Headed home/To a different timezone.” In the music video, Shake dials up the violence, but drops the romantic themes as she depicts a physical fight that takes place woods between herself and one of her male friends. After the fight which gets ugly to the point of spitting, the video ends with the whole group hanging out in their New Jersey neighborhood like nothing’s wrong. Maybe the fight was just about toughening one another up, or finding an outlet for external rage?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;Post__spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of ways places to put you rage, it’s getting borderline in here. Despite clouds of THC vapor, no one is chill. Shake is grandstanding about loving our neighbors while a guy yells at his date for putting her fingers in his nose. We bounce and cheer to banger after banger, each one it’s own groovy cyborgian musical moment. A beer-soaked dude soaked slams into me and my inner punk launches itself into the moshing abyss. My anxiety and angst rolls off in blissful waves, til I make eye contact with a woman whose looking kinda upset. Next time my feet touch down I allow them to stick in the sugary residue of a spilled drink. Shake hits a crescendo with “Under the Moon” and then plays us out with “Violent Crimes,” the closing track on Kanye’s 2018 album “Ye” that first launched Shake and the 070 collective into the national spotlight. It’s the future, it’s the past, it’s the slow-moving semi-apocalyptic now. Keep slaying NJ. Work on your physical self-awareness if you can.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The music video for 070 Shake's song &quot;Pines&quot; includes a gnarly fight scene.</summary></entry></feed>