<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-27T21:57:43-04:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Live—Work</title><subtitle>Looking at ART; mainly navel-gazing</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Talking Trash</title><link href="/2022/09/12/talking-trash.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Talking Trash" /><published>2022-09-12T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-09-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/2022/09/12/talking-trash</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2022/09/12/talking-trash.html">&lt;p class=&quot;small italic&quot;&gt;
  Times change. Up until now, I’ve been using this project as one big art- and media-fueled identity project, excavating things to throw at the caving internal void where my &quot;identity politics&quot; and &quot;family history&quot; ought to be. However, I can no longer sustain the luxury of an ongoing identity crisis. It’s time to get out of my head.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small italic&quot;&gt;
  Me and the baby take long walks, past row houses and free stores, concrete and flowers and trash. &quot;This is the world,&quot; I tell him, though I know by the time he can understand me the world will be hotter, the climate more volatile, the environment more full of microplastics. I like to imagine the baby as an adult with part park-ranger, part hacker, part MacGyver-like adaptability, able to thrive despite the climate apocalypse. Yet it occurs to me that when it comes to my creative practice, I'm somehow &lt;strong&gt;not creative enough&lt;/strong&gt; to dream up work that gives life to my ideas without doing ecological harm. Unless I want to be a HUGE hypocrite, I need to figure out how to change.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small underlined italic&quot;&gt;
  So I enlist the help of two local artists who seem a lot further on that path than I am. On a balmy August night we got together over drinks. This is the gist of what was said:
  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;trash-talk__castor&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/trash-talk-castor-in-studio.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Jesse Castor, printmaker &amp;amp; multimedia artist.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;trash-talk__castor&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;trash-talk__thayer&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/trash-talk-thayer-photo.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Molly Thayer, recycled textile artist.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;trash-talk__thayer&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;q-would-you-mind-introducing-yourselves&quot;&gt;Q: Would you mind introducing yourselves?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jesse:&lt;/strong&gt; I’m a very curious person who is just trying to figure out how to make something that makes the world make sense to me. I’m from South Jersey, like an hour outside of Philly, and I live in South Philly. My pronouns are she/hers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Molly:&lt;/strong&gt; I’m just gonna go with what my Lex bio says, which is “I’m a recycled textile artist.” I’m also a person outside of that…who likes swimming. I’m from Massachusetts, outside of Boston, and I live in West Philly. I use any pronouns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;q-hows-life&quot;&gt;Q: How’s Life?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jesse:&lt;/strong&gt; Life is very interesting. I have had a lot of chaotic things happen to me this year, and even just this month alone, but despite all of the chaos and all of the impostor syndrome, I think I’m showing up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Molly:&lt;/strong&gt; Life is really hard right now, a lot of destruction, but also life is really magical and abundant too. High highs and low lows I’d say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;trash-talk__castor-work-1&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/trash-talk-castor_window-panes_2021.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Castor, &quot;Window Panes&quot;, 2021&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;trash-talk__castor-work-1&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;trash-talk__castor-work-2&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/trash-talk-castor-installation.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Installation view of several of Castor's prints, including a large scale Love Seat collograph print and reclaimed material sculpture of a rowhouse atop a cardboard podium&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;trash-talk__castor-work-2&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;q-what-kind-of-art-do-you-make-and-how-do-you-use-trash&quot;&gt;Q: What kind of art do you make, and how do you use trash?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jesse:&lt;/strong&gt; I’m a printmaker first and foremost. I do a lot of images of “things.” I do a lot of chairs and windows and row homes. That’s iconography that I always go back to because I like thinking about the ideas of home and comfort items and things that symbolize transition in life. Since having my entire practice change up I’ve been focusing on using the materials that I have. Lately I’ve been doing some collage, using old prints that have lost their purpose or their meaning. I also have a bunch of handmade paper that I made out of leaves and denim and all kinds of crazy stuff. And I was doing cardboard sculptures of row homes for a little while, inspired by this house that I moved out of this past winter that I called Mouse House. I had all these leftover supplies from moving and packing and trying to seal up all the holes in my house where all the mice were coming in, so that was really cathartic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Molly:&lt;/strong&gt; I make Trash Art. (laughs). TM. I like to make functional objects the most, especially ones that go on the body, or engage with the body, like furniture, shoes, clothes. Even if it’s going in a window, I still feel like it’s functional. I guess all art is functional, because it’s making you happy. Or making you something. I also make looms out of recycled materials, like bottle caps, peanut butter caps, frisbees, or anything around that size. I like to use my drill and just drill a bunch of holes and make a loom. I also use textiles, which are always scrap fabrics, so I guess it counts as trash. A lot of plastic, plastic bags, hard plastics, fishing rope, vegetable netting, fabric, twine, ribbon, really anything, everything, especially colorful stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;trash-talk__thayer-work-1&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/trash-talk-thayer-weaving.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Thayer. Weaving and loom table at a flea market.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;trash-talk__thayer-work-1&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;trash-talk__thayer-work-2&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/trash-talk-thayer-shirt.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Incorporating recycled textiles and other materials pushes the limits of what a shirt should be. Shirt and necklace by Thayer.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;trash-talk__thayer-work-2&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;q-why-do-you-use-trash&quot;&gt;Q: Why do you use trash?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jesse:&lt;/strong&gt; For a while I did fall into that mindset that comes from going to art school and hanging out with people who do go to galleries and museums, thinking “I need to make art that looks like this to be a fine artist”. But by the end of my time there, it just wasn’t the thing that was making me happy. So I went back to doing what I know, which is using what I have at my disposal: repurposed or reclaimed items that I have found and repurposed, or found visually interesting and translated it into something that it reminded me of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Molly:&lt;/strong&gt;  I didn’t feel like I could be an artist growing up, but I always did sh*t. I would take my bathing suits and cut them up and turn them into different bathing suits, and just go in my room and be like  “grrr” *flex* and I’d show them to my mom and she’d be like “don’t rip your clothes up.” And then I went to college and was like, finally out of my parents wrath! My first winter term at Oberlin, I was on YouTube and found out about weaving with plastic bags and about plarn (To define “plarn”: “plastic + yarn = plarn”). I started making looms using cardboard, which, if you learn about weaving on YouTube, you’re gonna be making a cardboard loom. I made a bunch of big weavings using plarn, and I was just like “it’s over, it’s over for these h*s!” I felt like I had just cracked the code to life. I don’t know why I thought to do recycled art. I just wanted to. It’s so freaking accessible, free, queer, neurodivergent. The pedagogy — I love the word ‘pedagogy’ — of recycled materials is so freaking amazing. It asks you to play and communicate and transform, and change cultural meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--wide&quot; id=&quot;trash-talk__filthadelphia&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/trash-talk-litter-fairhill-annsbury.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Dumping at Fairhill and Annsbury streets in North Philadelphia, as reported to Philly 311 on March 8, 2022. (Twitter/@PHILLY311PHOTOS), is super commonplace, despite all the love people have for their communities.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;trash-talk__filthadelphia&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;q-we-live-in-philly-which-been-endearingly-described-as-a-trash-tornado-or-filthadelphia-how-do-you-feel-about-that&quot;&gt;Q: We live in Philly, which been endearingly described as a “trash tornado” or “Filthadelphia”. How do you feel about that?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jesse:&lt;/strong&gt; It’s funny, coming from somewhere so close by in New Jersey that it’s essentially a Philly suburb, and then moving into the city, I remember my parents being like “Why do you want to go to Philly? It’s so dirty, and people are so mean”, and this that and the other. And I’m like, “First of all, what am I gonna do, stay in New Jersey?!” Living in the area of South Philly that I am, the neighborhood is dirty, there is that trash tornado… but I feel like the longer I live here the more I see that there’s more to it than meets the eye. There are communities that get together and work around making their areas better. My neighborhood just recently got together and had a community cleanup. So I have a lot of respect for Filthadelphia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Molly:&lt;/strong&gt; How I feel about it is sad. That there is trash everywhere, there is so much pollution, and it’s centered on communities that are already suffering the most from other issues that are going on in society. But there is such a cool entrepreneurial reuse culture here. People will just do weird sh*t with weird materials just like off the side of their houses. There are a bunch of amazing organizations dealing with trash in Philly. Just to name-drop a few, we’ve got &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.muralarts.org/artworks/trash-academy/?gclid=CjwKCAjwpqCZBhAbEiwAa7pXeRy7_IWKGoovBvsXXCUi1n0fR_asu44p0gytfEZ9ITeG5Cs2USBKjxoCrw4QAvD_BwE&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Trash Academy&lt;/a&gt;, which is a part of Mural Arts, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rabbitrecycling.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Rabbit Recycling&lt;/a&gt; is a niche recycling company, and they don’t exist many places in the US. And then there’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rairphilly.org&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;RAIR&lt;/a&gt; the recycled arts residency, and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://tyler.temple.edu/queer-materials-lab&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Queer Materials Lab&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://fabscrap.org/philadelphia&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Fabscrap&lt;/a&gt; also just moved to Philly.  This is the stuff I’m a huge nerd about so I’ve found everything you can find and tried to work for every goddamn last one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;q-fine-art-is-traditionally-a-luxury-industry-what-does-it-feel-like-to-be-making-fine-art-out-of-trash-do-you-feel-like-trash-art-belongs-all-the-places-that-fine-art-belongs-do-you-make-fine-art&quot;&gt;Q: Fine art is traditionally a luxury industry. What does it feel like to be making fine art out of trash? Do you feel like trash art belongs all the places that fine art belongs? Do you make fine art?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Molly:&lt;/strong&gt; I make fine art. My art is fine. Trash Art deserves to be anywhere any other art is, but I don’t really care for it to be, nor am trying for it to be. I feel like I’m completely outside of that world. I have ADHD, museums are not my happy place. Even art galleries with all the hipsters, it’s like, “I’m confused.” I like things that are in the real world. Your question made me smile because trash can absolutely be so luxe and so fancy with doing very little. All you have to do is carefully deconstruct and clean it. I see the objects I work with as just beautiful objects that aren’t trash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jesse:&lt;/strong&gt; I don’t think Trash Art &lt;em&gt;needs&lt;/em&gt; to be made for the purpose of being Fine Art but I absolutely think that it is Fine Art. I don’t think it needs to be based around the material that you work in for it to be &lt;em&gt;museum quality&lt;/em&gt;. It’s always been a very imaginative process, as opposed to something that is like “I’m going to see this thing and recreate exactly what’s in front of me”. And I feel like that’s exactly what fine art is about. It’s about that exploration, that discovery that things are maybe a little bit different than what you perceived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;trash-talk__castor-scaffolds&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/trash-talk-castor_scaffolds_2021.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Castor, &quot;Scaffolds&quot;, 2021&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;trash-talk__castor-scaffolds&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;trash-talk__thayer-headpiece&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/trash-talk-thayer-headpiece.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Thayer. A headpiece made out of recycled netting&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;trash-talk__thayer-headpiece&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;q-lately-ive-been-starting-to-question-whether-the-way-i-make-art-is-authentic-to-my-lifestyle-and-the-society-we-live-in-my-life-is-pretty-planet-conscious-and-i-usually-enjoy-things-with-some-history-to-them--but-when-i-go-to-make-my-art-i-feel-like-i-need-to-buy-new-things-paint-brushes-canvas-chemicals-in-my-mind-that-sacrifice-feels-like-a-way-of-showing-love&quot;&gt;Q: Lately I’ve been starting to question whether the way I make art is authentic to my lifestyle and the society we live in. My life is pretty planet-conscious and I usually enjoy things with some history to them — but when I go to make my art I feel like I need to buy new things: paint, brushes, canvas, chemicals. In my mind that sacrifice feels like a way of showing love.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;but-listening-to-you-both-talk-about-your-art-even-when-you-work-with-trash-it-feels-like-you-love-your-materials-just-as-much&quot;&gt;But listening to you both talk about your art, even when you work with trash, it feels like you love your materials just as much.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jesse:&lt;/strong&gt; OH Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Molly:&lt;/strong&gt; OH MY GOD Yeah. Literally, I’ll find something squished on the pavement, covered in dirt, and pick it up and dust it off with my fingers and shove it in my pocket and get home and place it next to my other objects. It’s like pure love and adoration. And also another thing I don’t like is art stores. It’s so f*cking expensive. Don’t find me in a Blick, I won’t be there! I like things that are free, it’s easy, you find them on the street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jesse:&lt;/strong&gt; Part of why I love trash so much is the challenge of it. I was picking up pizza boxes off the side of the road to make my actual thesis for my fancy art school degree, and I hung it on the gallery walls and they were like “Are you kidding me?!” and I was like “Yeah my podium’s made out of cardboard boxes. What, I’m not gonna build a podium. Like, I had cardboard boxes and I had duct tape b*tch.” So that’s what I did. I made this with my hands, and you have to take it. It’s something that’s empowering to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;q-traditionally-the-art-world-is-not-very-planet-conscious-and-theres-even-a-kind-of-old-school-machismo-about-using-toxic-supplies-do-you-see-things-changing-from-where-you-stand&quot;&gt;Q: Traditionally the art world is not very planet-conscious, and there’s even a kind of old-school machismo about using toxic supplies. Do you see things changing from where you stand?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jesse:&lt;/strong&gt;  Where I went, PAFA, even though it inches its way into the mainstream, is still a very classical institution. I think the biggest leap PAFA ever made was to use odorless spirits instead of turpentine — odorless spirits are still not good for you. The classical forms of printmaking, like etching, where you’re using full on acid baths to etch metal plates, and acetone, and especially lithography has tons of &lt;em&gt;deathly chemicals&lt;/em&gt;. But that’s so true for so many types of artists. Every time I see an artist past 80 who still works in pastels, I’m like “you’re crazy”. Pastel dust super toxic, it gets stuck in your lungs. We still don’t know a ton of it. There are new materials coming out all the time. Acrylic paint is so new, we have no idea of the longterm impacts of it, we don’t know how conservation is going to be for it, and that’s just another instance of plastic making its way into the mainstream. I don’t know what the future holds for environmentally conscious art supplies, other than just trash. I would love to know. I should look that up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--large&quot; id=&quot;trash-talk__trash-academy&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/trash-talk-trash-academy-planter.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;A planter designed by Trash Academy project, and offshoot of Philadelphia Mural Arts&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;trash-talk__trash-academy&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;q-do-you-think-artists-specifically-have-a-role-in-the-climate-crisis-perhaps-to-help-people-imagine-a-different-future&quot;&gt;Q: Do you think artists specifically have a role in the climate crisis? Perhaps to help people imagine a different future?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jesse:&lt;/strong&gt; I think everybody has a role in the environmental crisis. I think it’s something that’s on everybody’s minds all the time, no matter what you do or where you are. My first experiences with repurposing materials didn’t come from an environmental concern, but I find a lot of solace in nature, and I want to be able to do my part, so as an artist I’ll do what I can. But I don’t think I necessarily hold every artist to that same belief. I don’t think every artist needs to be doing something specifically for the purpose of environmental conservation or political activism. I think all those things make their way into art whether you want them to or not, just because art is us. We are our art and our art is us. Whatever you’re making, even if it’s abstract is always a reflection of what you’re feeling and thinking about, whether that’s politics or the environment or your boyfriend just broke up with you — all of that stuff just kind of comes through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Molly:&lt;/strong&gt; I definitely think of my practice as being in and for the Apocalypse. The apocalypse being the one that is currently happening and the one that will continue to happen. As an artist, and I do want to push these things. I’m not a math guy, I’m not a reading guy, I just like shapes and textures and stuff like that. I can’t not think about community when I think about my art practice. I just want it to be an interactive, collaborative thing, and I just want everyone to be expressing, man!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;q-if-there-wasnt-an-apocalypse-do-you-think-youd-still-use-trash&quot;&gt;Q: If there wasn’t an apocalypse do you think you’d still use trash?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jesse:&lt;/strong&gt;  It’s hard to say. I think at the end of the day, I just love the challenge of changing something from what I knew it was into something different; and, no matter what material I’m working with, I’m always going to be striving to be doing that. Even if I bought a brand new tube of oil paint, I’d try to make it do something it wouldn’t usually be used for. At the end of the day maybe I made a difference, maybe not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Molly:&lt;/strong&gt; How would I know what life would be like if we weren’t living in an apocalypse? That would mean that life would be completely different. But I mean the act of picking something up and making something out of it… I think I would always be using found materials, [but maybe it would mean something different]. Everything is just a material from the world. Even the concept of a recycled material is silly. Everything has had a life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--large&quot; id=&quot;trash-talk__the-garden&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/trash-talk-castor-modeling-thayer.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Jesse models one of Molly's designs, a dress made from onion bags.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;trash-talk__the-garden&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Do artists have a responsibility in the Age of Trash? Can trash be luxe? Chemical machismo, Filthadelphia, living for the Apocalypse &amp; more</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Feed Me</title><link href="/2022/07/24/feed-me-cassatt.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Feed Me" /><published>2022-07-24T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-07-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/2022/07/24/feed-me-cassatt</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2022/07/24/feed-me-cassatt.html">&lt;p class=&quot;small italic underlined&quot;&gt;
  It took me time to see Mary Cassatt. And then she saw me. The following is a bit of a love-letter:
  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;Post__spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;feed-me__cassatt-childs-bath&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/feed-me-cassatt-the-childs-bath.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;A painting showing an aerial view of a woman bathing a young child with a pitcher and basin&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&quot;The Child’s Bath&quot; by Mary Cassatt, Oil on Canvas, 1893. Art Institute Chicago. ref. 1910.2&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;feed-me__cassatt-childs-bath&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;Post__spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mary Cassatt is a familiar fixture if you’ve heard of Impressionism. She painted a lot of women and children, achieved a high degree of realism, mainly interiors. She was the lone female painter that was allowed to join the official group of Impressionists, but that didn’t really matter to me one way or the other. I just knew her color palette wasn’t as bold as Monet’s, her subjects weren’t as exciting or varied as Manet’s, neither were her stylistic experiments as dramatic as Cezanne’s. By picking traditional feminine subjects, in darkened rooms, looking demurely away, Cassatt seemed determined to conform to and even celebrate the confines of gender roles under the patriarchy. Maybe that’s what she needed to do to survive, but I couldn’t manage to get excited about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I started painting more, I began to appreciate Cassatt’s technical mastery. Her artwork has this unbelievable way of wrangling squirming humanity into an ordered harmony without bludgeoning it into taxidermy-like submission. Even today, a Cassatt painting caputures living, breathing humanity much better than a Live Photo or a Boomerang or other contrivance of photographic technology. The drawing is accurate, but the brush strokes are loose and painterly, responding to the texture and illumination of the surface she describes. All of these contradictions she effortlessly balances on a knife’s edge. To me it’s hypnotic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still found her subject matter tired and unrelatable as I started working and my extended family aged and drifted. I continued to change, making things along the way. I lost a lot of the internalized sexism that I’d held on to as a girl who growing up in male-dominated spaces (punk rock, art collectives, computer engineering). I had a baby, and suddenly had to care for it. The rhythm of these rituals seeped into my life and sense of self. And through doing that work myself, in all its bloody, sweaty and tenacious glory, I started to wonder if Cassatt’s paintings weren’t really celebrating the Romanticism of Motherhood after all. In contrast to all the airbrushed photos that fill mommy-blogs, Cassatt’s work seemed to be the opposite of sensationalized. One hundred years later her work felt strikingly realistic. And I wondered if in fact her real goal was to celebrate mothers and caregivers as workers. To try to show the male-dominated art world the quiet heroism of female domestic labor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;feed-me__rivera-detroit-industry&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/feed-me-rivera-auto-workers-mural.png&quot; alt=&quot;A mural depicting workers in an automobile factory&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;From Detroit Industry murals, one of twenty-seven fresco panels at the Detroit Institute of the Arts by Diego Rivera, 1932-33.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;feed-me__rivera-detroit-industry&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;feed-me__modern-women&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/feed-me-cassatt-modern-women.png&quot; alt=&quot;An illustration of adolescent and young adult women picking apples together in Victorian garb&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Colored engraving after &quot;Modern Woman — Young Women Plucking the Fruits of Knowledge or Science&quot; (1893) by Mary Cassatt (image via Wikimedia)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;feed-me__modern-women&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it going to far to paint Cassatt as a feminist? No way. Experience trying to survive in male-dominated spaces would tell you she’d be just as likely to advocate for the advancement of other women as to be one of those annoying “I’ve-got-mine-now-you-get-yours” types who see other talented women as a threat, but she was definitely the former. Check out Cassatt’s (suspiciously destroyed/lost) mural for the Women’s Pavilion at the 1893 Chicago World’s Columbian Exposition and you won’t doubt it. She even had tons of talented female contemporaries (I caught an exhibition called Women In Motion at PAFA that was dedicated to several of them). Cassatt never married or had children, perhaps believing (not irrationally) that the duties of wife and motherhood might preclude her ability to work as a painter, but she spent a lot of time with women who did take a more traditional path. Unable to work from the nude figure like male artists did,Cassatt made the non-traditional choice to focus on the vantage point she was allowed to access: that of domestic female spaces. Day after day, Cassatt saw women bathe, hold, cajole, and feed tiny humans, and elevated these mundane tasks to the level fine art. These depictions are not stuffy vanity portraits of rich families and their angelic children — they’re real, they do show the work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, as a new mom, sweaty and exhausted and struggling to feed my newborn at 3am while my partner slept, I wondered if anyone saw me, maybe Cassatt did. Her work seemed to say that she saw us, the body-feeders as though we were as hard-working and heroic and dependable as Diego Rivera’s socialist motor workers in a Detroit factory. It felt nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;Post__spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;body-feeding&quot;&gt;Body-Feeding&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s it been like learning to be a bodyfeeder?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physical, emotional, and round-the clock. And completely different from the work done in my professional life, where I’m a web developer at an agency. At the agency, there are agreed-upon hours, contracts, coworkers, variety; the work is creative and intellectual. The work/life balance is good, and if it wasn’t I could work somewhere else, or negotiate. I’m good at it, and if I wasn’t, someone else could do the job instead. By contrast, body feeding has none of this translatable flexibility. Our biology seems to prefer a “one-baby, one feeder” relationship — lactation is an ability only unlocked by birth, and furthermore the amount of milk produced is carefully calibrated between the baby and feeder via supply and demand. Feeding work is &lt;em&gt;essential.&lt;/em&gt; This might sound romantic and self-important but it also means that someone else has a claim on your body and its labor. &lt;em&gt;Essential&lt;/em&gt; things must be done when they need to be done, leaving the worker vulnerable to overwork and burnout. “The worker” being me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The feeding job began immediately, in that raw, postpartum haze. At first I was really bad at it, and found the schedule relentless. Newborns need to eat every 2 hours, and they drink slow. If a REM cycle is 3 hours, how do you like those sleep prospects? I knew almost nothing about nursing, but since all mammals did it, I assumed it was relatively easy. There wasn’t really family knowledge I could access. I knew from old letters that my mom had been pretty solidly in the pro-formula camp (despite oligopoly in the formula industry and the non-trivial cost, I think her generation saw it as a feminist coup, allowing other people to share in the feeding duties). My mom’ sister said something to the effect of “it’s too hard, you’ll never make it” when she heard I planned to body-feed (she was a physician in the 90s and early otts). I also found most internet literature pretty unhelpful. Either it was some obnoxiously twee Earth-Mama lifestyle content, or yet another SEO-optimized version of The Four Nursing Holds (cradle hold! cross-cradle! side-lying! football!) that simply glossed over the many other hard parts, such as latching, how to tell when the baby is hungry or has a lip-tie or wants to suckle for a sleep-aid or comfort. The first effective nursing position I stumbled on you might call the “fiddler crab”. It involved keeping my right forearm tightly flexed holding the baby’s entire body while I pinched my left nipple to make it as small and pointy as possible, to fit a newborn’s tiny mouth. This was only minorly effective and gave me back-aches. I spent many interim hours lying flat on the floor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took practice to even reach fiddler crab status. Over and over again I’d try to get my baby to latch, and instead of drinking, they would spit out the nipple, or choke and spit out the nipple, or worst lethargically drowse off without drinking anything at all. This was bad because if a baby doesn’t regularly latch and drink the pre-milk (called colostrum) your body won’t get any cues to start producing The Good Stuff in the next 3-5 days. Days passed and the baby steadily lost weight — 3%, 5%, 7.6%, then 9.5%. Loss of 10% of birth weight means doctors will start pressuring you to supplement with formula. And not to judge anyone who chooses to use formula, but I didn’t want that. This was the plan, and I felt if I failed, I’d be letting my baby, my partner, my midwife, to some degree my whole extended community, down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, I had help. My midwife asked another mom in our community to donate a bit of her pumped milk, and gave us a syringe to administer it in order to “perk up” the baby if they started sleeping through meals. She also referred us to a lactation consultant who gave me some remedial “latching lessons”, and told me how to use a pump to get a milk supply going. She encouraged me as I struggled through that first tough week and within 7 days the baby was back up to birth weight! We were out of the woods. Soon I was spending a lot of (quality?) time with the baby, transferring milk. 8 to 12 times per day, 10 to 20 minutes at a time (not counting the minutes the baby takes a break and isn’t drinking). Sitting patiently, or impatiently. Dozing. Thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;feed-me__matrix&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/feed-me-matrix.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;A brown-haired man sits in a pod of orange gel with tubes in his main arteries&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;In the Matrix, Neo wakes up and views the bodies-to-energy machine to which he is connected&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;feed-me__matrix&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;calories-of-power&quot;&gt;Calories of Power&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does it change me? Sure. At first it makes me feel like a piece of furniture, like my friend’s automatic cat feeder. Food goes in, milk comes out, roughly 500 calories worth every day. It don’t have much say in the matter, if I want my spawn to grow up big and strong. This non-consent is unsettling, like I’m one of those bodies hooked up to tubes in &lt;em&gt;The Matrix&lt;/em&gt;. As energy is siphoned out of my body, powerful waves of thirst or hunger remind me that although I am no longer pregnant, still my body is not my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I listen to a lot of podcasts while latch-trapped. On one of them I learn about Anglo-Saxon feasting culture. In premodern Britain, local men (men) would be invited to witness the lord’s power, in the form of bottomless food, and gorge themselves. By eating at the lord’s table they got a better meal than they were used to, and in doing so declared themselves grateful and therefor loyal to said lord. You can spin this factoid any way you want, but at the heart I think it’s interesting that care for the body in the form of food was these lords’ chosen vehicle for forming a basis for their power. Not any other base need; FOOD. Not violent taking; generous GIVING.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still though, feeding someone is giving on another level. It isn’t like buying carbon offsets or giving to a rent relief fund, or being a sustaining member of NPR. As I see the look of pure worship that my baby wears when they see their favorite person (Left Boobie! though Right Boobie is a close second) I can’t help but think of my body as an extraction site, a landscape. The implications of this make me uneasy. In high school social studies, a teacher taught us that extractive economic activities basically always exist at a power disadvantage to all economic activities that occur downstream of them — even though they are only made possible by the extraction in the first place. I’m not a capitalist so I don’t really get why, but anyone can see it proven true if they compare the build cycle and profit distribution patterns for any product. Whether it’s an iPhone, a movie or a pair of jeans it’s always the same. Everyone knows the cotton farmer or miner of rare earths is getting ripped off. The creatives are given just enough to keep them selling their ideas, while the investors and executives who don’t make anything at all walk off with most of the profit. The landscape itself is thanklessly plundered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tired as I am, I really do feel lucky. Despite being more sustainable and cost-effective, in the United States rates of body-feeding are actually higher among wealthier, more educated Americans, and I appreciate the resources and support that helped get me here. Friends and family descend to help us adjust, cooking, cleaning, going up and down the stairs while I’m recovering. It feels poetic that, as I’m pouring myself out to feed the newborn, others are feeding me. When I’m at a breaking point I try to remind myself of this. I try not to sulk openly too often, while everyone basks in the new-baby glow. I feel like it’s the least I can do. When our overflowing fridge at last empties out I watch my partner drink Soylent as an afternoon pick-me-up. It strikes me Soylent is a kind of VC-backed (vegan) adult breastmilk, mass-produced for infantile adults who’d rather stare at a screen than participate in food culture. I don’t say it out loud because my partner is actually a good cook and these days I’m vocally arguing with him about almost everything else. One night he tries some of The Good Stuff straight from the source. He says it’s really sugary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;feed-me__nursing&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/feed-me-cassatt-young-mother-nursing-her-child.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;A painting of a brown haired woman breastfeeding a baby who reaches up and touches her chin&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&quot;Young Mother Nursing Her Child&quot;. Mary Cassatt (American, 1844–1926), Oil on Canvas, 1906. Art Institute Chicago (deaccessioned) ref. 1956.760&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;feed-me__nursing&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;symbiosis&quot;&gt;Symbiosis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The baby gained physical health quickly, but our relationship took a bit longer. Feeding was this intimate space that me and the baby now could access, but neither of us exactly felt safe in there. I felt open to attack, and the baby felt like I was withholding essential calories they needed to survive. I gave as much as I could, but not quite willingly. The baby received the nutrition, but not quite gratefully. At times it felt low-key traumatic, all forced limbs, tiny fingernails, red-faced baby-tears. It was not the foundation I wanted for me and my child. But there was a glimmer of hope. Rarely, usually in the dead of night, I’d respond to the baby’s hungry-cry and they’d open their eyes and magically be calm and patient. Slowly, I’d plop them on my chest. Squinty-eyed, they’d fumble, until they found the milk they were looking for, and drank til they were full. They didn’t howl or scratch, so I never had to grab their head and manually latch them (some people swear by this method, my baby hates it). I felt respected, so I let them take their time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the baby and I were to continue as body-feeding partners, this is how I wanted it to be. We were partners in a way. We didn’t have language, and I held most of the power, but I could listen and respond with my actions. To preserve my self-respect, I set up ground rules with the baby. I would feed willingly when they asked, but if they started having a tantrum there would be a time-out, and myself or someone else would gently calm them down. As cranky and sleep-deprived as I was, I started to realize the baby might be cranky and tired too, so we started helping them nap more. That was huge. It’s not always perfect, but mostly it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I took away from this, the most ordinary of miracles, is that symbiosis is a choice. It’s basic, but it feels really applicable when I think about the ways other relationships in my life have failed or succeeded, be they activist coalitions, working partnerships, relationships with neighbors. The kinds of relationships we rely upon to survive. The thing about our species is there is no “default setting”. Reproduce, or not. Caretake, or not. Body-feed, or feed another way (fed is best). Dominate, or coexist. We choose the work we want to do in the world, and that in turn makes the world we give future generations to work in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;Post__spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;smallness&quot;&gt;Smallness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the baby, my world has become suddenly very small, but also deep. Small moments have meaning. My baby won’t remember the relationship we had when it revolved around body-feeding them, and maybe I won’t either. But maybe we’ll remember how it felt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want them to remember the feeling that the world is abundant, but not infinite. To know what it feels like to be sated, so they don’t resort to gluttony or greed. To know what it feels like to be cared for so they’ll know how to care for themself and others. I also want them to be scrappy and to tread on the Earth lightly. It feels somewhat reckless to be bringing a new human into the world when I know they’ll have to grapple with a climate crisis, but it would feel awfully pessimistic not to, and so it’s important to me that the way in which we’re doing it be a vote for the kind of world I want my kid to be born into. As a techno-minimalist (tech is cool, products are fine, but if you don’t need to buy it let’s give the Earth a break) things like not owning a car, body-feeding, using cloth diapers are part of that. Not that any of it is enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all this I’m happy to do the work. The kind you do every day because it needs to be done, not because it’s celebrated, because you’re who’s there and you know it matters. I’m even proud to. And maybe Mary Cassatt is proud of us too. I hope she had enough people being proud of her in her time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;feed-me__cassatt-photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/feed-me-mary-cassatt-1914.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;A black and white photo of a gray-haired white woman wearing a feathered hat, fur coat and long beaded necklace&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Mary Cassatt in 1914&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;feed-me__cassatt-photo&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It took me time to see Mary Cassatt. And then she saw me. The following is a bit of a love-letter...</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">CUT + PRINT</title><link href="/2020/08/12/cut-and-print.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CUT + PRINT" /><published>2020-08-12T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-08-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/2020/08/12/cut-and-print</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/08/12/cut-and-print.html">&lt;p class=&quot;small underlined&quot;&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Lately I've become obsessed with the idea that you can write your own history (instead of waiting around for the powers-that-be to decide what &quot;history&quot; is). I rembered my friend Sen telling me they participated in something called the Queer Ancestors Project, so called them up and asked them a bunch of questions about it!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;The following transcript has been edited for length and clarity:&lt;/em&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alicia Willett:&lt;/strong&gt; In 2019 you were part of a printmaking workshop called The Queer Ancestors Project, where you discovered your own Queer ancestors and made artwork that told the story of them and of you. How did you become involved?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sen Lu:&lt;/strong&gt; I think I found the Queer Ancestors Project from an ad on Instagram, and it was billed as a free linocut workshop for Queer people aged 18-26 with any range of experience in linocut printing. I’ve always had some level of impostor syndrome around the idea of doing art, because I think the way I was raised was very anti-pursuing-art-as-a-career and also anti-hobby. It allowed me to put everything into what I was working on and really invest in it because there was a goal [(the closing reception)] and then afterwards start divesting from having goals in my art practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AW:&lt;/strong&gt; What was being in the program like?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SL:&lt;/strong&gt; We had some structure and some freedom. We had to make four prints. For the first print we had to just pick a queer ancestor, and we also had a visit to the GLBT archives which are super fucking cool!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SL:&lt;/strong&gt; I started out wanting to look into Queer Asian history, because I don’t really know much about Asian American history, let alone Queer Asian American history, and I think I had a lot of assumptions based on my experiences growing up: that Asian American activism was all like, shitty assimilationist politics, since the suburb that I grew up in was very much like “Chinese Americans Against Affirmative Action” type activism. Being in the Bay Area I’m starting to realize that there’s a really really deep history of radical Asian American Activism and radical Queer Asian American Activism that I was really close to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AW:&lt;/strong&gt; The Queer Ancestors Project has an &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;quot;https://www.queerancestorsproject.org/2019-2020-artists&amp;quot;&quot;&gt;online gallery&lt;/a&gt; featuring work from participants over the years. It’s so clear that each artist has a story to tell and a unique way of using linocut to do that. Could I ask you talk about the prints you made?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;sen__phoenix-rising&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/sen-phoenix-rising.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Two phoenixes swoop down to attach an unseen adversary, one with a sharp beak, the other with sharp talons.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Sen 森. Phoneix Rising. Linocut on paper. 2019. Phoenix Rising was the name of the first known Queer Asian/Pacific American newsletter, established in 1984 in San Franciso. In Chinese culture, a fenghuang (phoenix) carries connotations of feminine energy.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;sen__phoenix-rising&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SL:&lt;/strong&gt; [“Phoenix Rising”] was the first print I ever did, and it was also the first time I’d done art in like, forever. I really wanted to do Asian imagery, and I think it was my first time incorporating Asian imagery into any artwork I was doing. One thing I wanted to do in that piece was [play with] the fenghuang (phoenix) and the dragon pairing. They are a really traditional heterosexual Chinese pairing, like yin and yang, or the emperor and the empress, man and wife. There’s some implication that the phoenix is pure and delicate and the dragon is strong and can attack, and in having two phoenixes as a pair instead I really wanted them to be interdependent, like, I didn’t want there to be a power dynamic. The way I portrayed them I wanted them to be both attacking an unseen opponent and both defending each other. I think that represents the kind of “For Us, By Us” [attitude] I’d like to see in our community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AW:&lt;/strong&gt; What was it like meeting your Queer Ancestors?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SL:&lt;/strong&gt; I got to meet two elders in person, one was Giselle Cohan, and she was one of the co-founders of Phoenix Rising, which was the first Asian American Lesbian newsletter in the United States, and it was basically a publication they’d send out monthly for several years. It had picnics, or like news about a gathering in the forest a bunch of Asian Queers did one weekend, and fundraisers and personals. It was super interesting because she works in tech [like me, and] the way she talks about herself she makes it seem like she has a pretty quiet life, despite [her involvement being] so seminal and so historical. [It] allowed me to unpack some of the guilt that I had about being here and being in tech and just the things that I was navigating. And then I also got meet Kitty Tsui, although we didn’t actually get to talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;sen__kitty&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/sen-kitty.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A muscular woman with short hair is shown from the waist up, looking over her right shoulder at the viewer. Swirling, colorful cross-hatched lines describe her body, in contrast with a stark rectangular frame and black background&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Sen 森. KITTY. Linocut on paper. 2019. Kitty Tsui (b. 1952, Hong Kong) is a Queer Bay-Area writer, bodybuilder, actor, artist and activist. A prolific writer whose works include WORDS OF A WOMAW WHO BREATHES FIRE, BREATHLESS – EROTICA and SPARKS FLY, Tsui is also a leather woman and a prize-winning bodybuilder.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;sen__kitty&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AW:&lt;/strong&gt; You honor Kitty Tsui eith a print as well. It’s a really powerful image, with bold square lines framing the powerful contours and textures of Tsui’s athletic body — a body that is literally busting out of the frame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In your artist’s statement you reference Tsui in 1996, “Growing up in Hong Kong, I heard all around me mothers yelling at their children: ‘Say nui, mo no, mo yung!’ Dead girl, no brain, no use… For me as an Asian/Pacific lesbian, silence is not an option. To ensure that we…be acknowledged as who we are. Women with a history…Women who survived being dead girls.” (“Asian Pacific Lesbian a.k.a Dead Girl, China Doll, Dragon Lady, or the Invisible Man”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you think it means to be a “dead girl”? I’ve never heard that phrase before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SL:&lt;/strong&gt; I’d never actually heard it before either. I think the way Kitty was talking about it was probably talking about pretty misogynistic culture, and I think in that sense Chinese culture is very misogynistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just found it in this Cantonese dictionary. There’s this term “bad girl,” like in the way you might say to you cat “You’re being a bad girl!” It’s an abusive term for a bad girl, and the characters in it are literally like “dead” “daughter” or “dead” “woman”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other day my mom sent me this photo of an old Chinese scroll that had like two poems and I asked her to translate them for me and she said the first poem is about raising a daughter and how your daughter is the most delicate flower that you spend all your days watering and it grows so beautiful and slender and delicate as possible, and one day a man comes and plucks it with no thanks to you! And then the second half is about raising a son, like raising a son is like opening a bank account that you deposit all your money into, and then one day this woman comes and just takes the whole bank account without any gratitude. And I’m like, ‘This is like so awful, why would you send me this??’ So I think there’s all this history of the one child policy and how there aren’t enough girls because everyone only wanted men, because they keep the family line going, etc. etc., and women aren’t necessarily supposed to be out there having their own opinions. It’s very confusing, I don’t really get it. But I think maybe that’s partially what it’s about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AW:&lt;/strong&gt; It also reminds me of the slogan from the AIDS crisis “Silence = Death”. Like if silence will kill you, speaking your truth might make you more alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SL:&lt;/strong&gt; I like that a lot. That reminds be a little bit of this Junot Diaz’s quote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“…if you want to make a human being into a monster, deny them, at the cultural level, any reflection of themselves. And growing up, I felt like a monster in some ways. I didn’t see myself reflected at all. I was like, “Yo, is something wrong with me? That the whole society seems to think that people like me don’t exist?” And part of what inspired me, was this deep desire that before I died, I would make a couple of mirrors. That I would make some mirrors so that kids like me might see themselves reflected back and might not feel so monstrous for it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;sen__ping-chang-xin&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/sen-inner-strength.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A portrait of a semi-nude figure sitting cross-legged, backed by a halo and a dragon.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Sen 森. 平常心 (píng cháng xīn). Translation: peace of mind, one's natural self, an unagitated mind. Linocut on paper. 2019. Composed in the style of thangka paintings that traditionally depict the Buddha, the dragon curled behing the halo represents the possible threats to one's peace of mind.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;sen__ping-chang-xin&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AW:&lt;/strong&gt; I think my favorite work from this series is your self portrait. It just gives off this intense aura of inner strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SL:&lt;/strong&gt; It’s styled after these paintings [called thanka paintings] that are hung throughout my aunt and grandmother’s homes that are from the Tibetan buddhist tradition.usually portraying the Buddha near a place that you would pray, to help you think about all the Buddha-like qualities and aspire to embody them in yourself. I added an eastern-style dragon that was wrapped around the halo, which also looks like a bubble or a protective circle. I wanted to make it unclear whether the dragon was protecting me or trying to harm me, to symbolize my relationship with my feelings. I was in a place in my life where I was realizing, despite thinking that I took time to feel my feelings every day, in retrospect I was actually pretty dissociated from them. My partner had mentioned that it would take me a long time to process my feelings, or I wouldn’t be even aware that I was feeling certain ways, like angry or defensive, [or] reacting in a triggered way. I had this sort of fantasy of myself as a person who was completely aware of my feelings and in control. And so it was also about that journey and trying to unpack my relationship with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then part of it was I think me trying to get more comfortable with my body, which is why I did a nude self portrait. I definitely have and continue to have a lot of internalized fat-phobia and I think it’s something I really want to work on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AW:&lt;/strong&gt; Are you saying you are your own ancestor in a way, that you’re your own God?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SL:&lt;/strong&gt; Something we talked about a lot during the workshop was “Who are your Queer Ancestors?”  I think the notion of family has always been a really difficult one for me because I don’t feel like I have “Family’ in the way that maybe the Western tradition conditions you to think about what family should mean. And I think in terms of Queer role models, my elders and role models are mainly just my friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t really have my own gods. My own spirituality is very made-up and very personalized to me. I draw from a lot of different influences. There’s no one person or people that I am able to pattern-match when it comes to what I want out of my life. I think a lot of the people my parents would like me to think of as role models are really antithetical to the things that I want. I don’t really have professional mentors, or people that I admire who are in a mentorship position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think there’s an aspect of loneliness to it too that I’m really only reflecting on now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;sen__qap-reception&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/sen-qap-reception.png&quot; alt=&quot;A crowded room packed with young adults looking at artwork hanging on the wall.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Participants in the Queer Ancestors Project exhibit their work at a closing reception.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;sen__qap-reception&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AW:&lt;/strong&gt; How was the closing reception?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SL:&lt;/strong&gt; It felt really good. It was such a trip. It was really packed, and it was really interesting to have people come up to me and say ”Wow, your art made me think about these things,” which was really sweet. Katie [Gilmartin, printmaker and creator of the Queer Ancestors Program] said one of her favorite parts about being the featured artist is you can talk to anyone you want at the entire event, and you’ll always have an excuse to do so, and I loved that, it’s so true. And as somebody who likes being able to meet people and not having to deal with social pressures or cues it was great to be able to show up at this thing, dress however the fuck I want. It was my first time really being in “the art world” and knowing without the shadow of a doubt that I could take up as much space as I wanted, and that made a lot of sense in the room.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AW:&lt;/strong&gt; That’s so inspirational. I think there are definitely lessons in there that I’m trying to learn… Do you think you found what you were looking for here?
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SL:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, I think so! Maybe instead of feeling less like an impostor I feel I care less about the idea that there are rules or that there’s an institution I’m trying to break into. Right now I’m in a place where I’m trying to figure out what comes next!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--small&quot; id=&quot;sen__selfie&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/sen-selfie.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A photo of Sen decorated with stickers and sparkles.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Sen is a Southern Californian of Taiwanese descent. They currently live in Oakland and work in tech. IG: @lv.sen&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;sen__selfie&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Lately I've become obsessed with the idea that you can write your own history (instead of waiting around for the powers-that-be to decide what &quot;history&quot; is). I rembered my friend Sen telling me they participated in something called the Queer Ancestors Project, so called them up and asked them a bunch of questions about it! The following transcript has been edited for length and clarity:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">FAKING DEEPLY</title><link href="/2020/07/26/faking-deeply.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FAKING DEEPLY" /><published>2020-07-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/2020/07/26/faking-deeply</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/07/26/faking-deeply.html">&lt;p class=&quot;small italic underlined&quot;&gt;
  To what degree is your history required to be true?
  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
  At a time when America is trying to put the final nails in the coffin of the Lost Cause myth by purging confederate flags, names and statues from public spaces, I’m increasingly obsessed with the idea that inventing a personal mythology could be a healing project...
  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;Post__spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This winter I picked up Jamaica Kincaid’s &lt;span class=&quot;text-underline&quot;&gt;The Autobiography of My Mother&lt;/span&gt; let’s say it had some unexpected emotional consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instantly, I was sucked into what I (I guess naïvely) thought was the autobiography of Kincaid’s mother. There was no introduction describing her methodology, but I assumed Kincaid had pieced together assorted documents, letters, and interviews with her mother to create a book-length memoir, either collaboratively while she was alive or more likely alone after her death. The novel is set in Dominica, and although I knew Kincaid was from Antigua, I just assumed that her mother had moved later in life. If there were a couple of narrative elements that were too well-crafted to be real, well I assumed they were stylistic liberties taken to help give the story shape. The characters’ personalities just felt so real, their outer lives so unsentimentally “regular,” their inner lives convincingly reduced and hermetically sealed behind the memorable life events and remembered dialogue that survive in a personal account. Probably I just wanted to believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--wide&quot; id=&quot;faking__dominica&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/dominica_rosalie-via-google-maps.png&quot; alt=&quot;A Caribbean shoreline with driftwood on the sand and tropical forest in the distance&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Rosalie Bay, Dominica, via Google Street View on 07/27/2020&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;faking__dominica&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;True or not, this book wrecked me, and wrecked me worse when I discovered Kincaid had made it all up. Why would she do such a thing? The novel follows the life story of Xuela, a motherless girl of Caribe and African ancestry without wealth or influence, a woman no one would bother to keep a history of. Throughout the course of her life, the protagonist finds a way to build a whole self from the inadequate scraps afforded her in a society deeply damaged by colonialism. Defiantly, she chooses to love everything about that self, from her capacity for independent thought to her sexuality to her most pungent bodily odors, although she never fully manages to trust or love others. Imagining &lt;span class=&quot;text-underline&quot;&gt;The Autobiography of My Mother&lt;/span&gt; as nonfiction, I was able to experience Xuela’s story as one of great personal victory because, despite everything she isn’t given, in her own imperfect way she makes it, she ascends, and builds a life with much more love and much less hate than she inherited. Healing from intergenerational trauma feels much more possible in a world where Xuela’s story is true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not everyone sees Xuela with the same optimism, possibly because they don’t see themselves in Xuela in the same way that I do. My grandmother was a poor uneducated woman from a Caribbean nation and I know almost nothing about her life before coming to America. I wish I knew what choices she had made in her past lives that made her the vibrant person who cooked and fished and gardened and almost never sat down, who played Uno and wanted my sister and I to date many boys and loved movies starring Johnny Depp. I feel like I’d know more about my own potential somehow, if I knew the shape of the unknown power flowing in my veins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;faking__book&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/kincaid-autobiography-of-my-mother.png&quot; alt=&quot;A photo of the book&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Autobiography of My Mother, by Jamaica Kincaid&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;faking__book&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her 1996 New York Times review entitled “A World as Cruel as Job’s,” prolific author and book critic Cathleen Schine describes Kincaid’s novel as “inhuman, and unapologetically so,” viewing the protagonist as “the motley result of colonialism, defiled even in conception,” “willfully barren,” “defined by hatred,” her racial mixture a “parable of moral impurity”. She sees Xuela as inseparable from the constant low-grade neglect, exploitation and hatred that pervade her circumstances, rather than by all the choices she makes within those circumstances that outline the true shape of her humanity. Xuela cannot pretend the people in her life do not mistreat her, but her narration ensures we always understand the perpetrators are human, and their actions feel like the result of something they personally lack, rather than an inherently “evil” temperament. As a vulnerable youth, Xuela might act defensively, such as when she gave a poisoned necklace her stepmother meant for her to her stepmother’s dog, but as an adult we see her show cruel family members mercy, helping her unwed half sister have an abortion and caring for her after she is maimed in a bike accident; finding ways to love her father and her late brother. The fact that Schine can misread Kincaid so egregiously, that she is unable to look past the evidence of the damage done by her ancestors to see the humanity of the formerly colonized, shows how unreliable the history the victors provide can be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--wide&quot; id=&quot;faking__quote&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/watermelon-woman-quote.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sometimes you have to create your own history. The Watermelon woman is fiction. - Cheryl Dunye, 1996&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;faking__quote&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only thing to do in the wake of such an unreliable official history is to give ourselves permission to be creative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Director Cheryl Dunye really turned me onto the idea that we must write our own mythology with her very 90’s comedy &lt;em&gt;The Watermelon Woman&lt;/em&gt;, also released in 1996. Dunye stars as ‘Cheryl’, a Black lesbian video store employee and aspiring filmmaker, making a documentary about an early Hollywood actress named Fae Richards who delivered several stunning performances acting the part of an enslaved woman. As Cheryl interviews a series of people who knew or knew of this actress we learn as much about the interviewee’s relationship to history as we do about Richards. One person is an unorganized pack-rat, another an anal cinephile interested in every detail of ‘race films’ except the women. Several seek to downplay or erase the actress’s relationship with a white female director because of their own homophobic or more often segregationist attitudes. A women’s studies professor spends a weird scene insisting that the “mammy” and watermelon stereotypes are not bigoted because they can be viewed through the lens of her Italian grandmothers. Cheryl is obsessed with Richards, while her best friend, who is also a Black lesbian filmmaker, could not care less. We come away feeling there’s no such thing as impersonal history. History is something everyone needs to do for their self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;faking__dunye&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/watermelon-woman-cheryl.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cheryl films herself sitting in a chair talking to the camera. Behind her photos of Fae Richards are taped to the wall.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Cheryl films a scene for her documentary about'The Watermelon Woman'&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;faking__dunye&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;faking__dunye&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/watermelon-woman-cheryl.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cheryl films herself sitting in a chair talking to the camera. Behind her photos of Fae Richards are taped to the wall.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Cheryl films a scene for her documentary about'The Watermelon Woman'&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;faking__dunye&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;faking__richards-page&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/watermelon-woman-richards-and-page.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;An old photograph of two bohemian women relaxing in the grass with the caption 'Martha Page and Fae Richards, 1931'&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Cheryl Dunye invented Fae Richards, piecing her together from research about real Black actresses and performers in the 1930s&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;faking__richards-page&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder if Dunye and Kincaid ever talked. Both women made works in the 1990s that grapple with their histories, and both made works that try to repair something in their past that is broken. For Dunye it is the fact that she is trying to find her artistic voice in a medium that has historically excluded people like her. “Our stories have never been told,” Cheryl says at the beginning of movie, and she has no mentors or historical role models to help her find her way.  For Kincaid it is intergenerational trauma. How can a person avoid becoming a force that perpetuates the shame and neglect that colonialism has made her birthright? The weight of the past holds them back — in &lt;span class=&quot;text-underline&quot;&gt;The Autobiography of My Mother&lt;/span&gt; Xuela reflects “For me history was not only the past: it was the past and it was also the present… I did not see the future, and that is perhaps how it should be. Why should anyone see such a thing? And yet…and yet, it made me sad to know that I did not look straight ahead of me, I always looked back, and sometimes to the side, but mostly I looked back.” (p138-139)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By bending reality in this way Kincaid and Dunye each work a kind of magic on the probably unsolvable problem of how to get over your history. Unlike the myth of a noble confederacy, denial of the past is not the effect of these storytellers’ fabrications. In the stories Kincaid and Dunye tell, the spirit of the real history is there, if not the evidence. The purpose of their inventions is not to gaslight others about a shameful past, but to build a lens through which to see a more whole future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--large&quot; id=&quot;faking__richards-page&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/watermelon-woman-richards-and-page.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;An old photograph of two bohemian women relaxing in the grass with the caption 'Martha Page and Fae Richards, 1931'&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;faking__richards-page&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to Dunye for being so willing to put her struggles on film, to allow us to learn and stuggle with her. In 1992, Dunye wrote in the journal FELIX that the issues she deals with in her films “aren’t easy ones, and I struggle with them daily. Rather than internalizing them, I put them in my videos.” This willingness Dunye had to share her struggles as a new filmmaker opened my eyes to the idea that the past is not exactly set in stone. It’s a living thing, and if I find it devalues and erases me it can be nurtured into something else – whether it be like the life of Fae Richards or the &lt;span class=&quot;text-underline&quot;&gt;The Autobiography of My Mother&lt;/span&gt; or something comepletely different – a place from which I can imagine a future where I feel whole.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">To what degree is your history required to be true? At a time when America is trying to put the final nails in the coffin of the Lost Cause myth by purging confederate flags, names and statues from public spaces, I’m increasingly obsessed with the idea that inventing a personal mythology could be a healing project...</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">EVERYTHING IS AN ECHO OF ITSELF</title><link href="/2020/05/14/labyrinths.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EVERYTHING IS AN ECHO OF ITSELF" /><published>2020-05-14T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/2020/05/14/labyrinths</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/05/14/labyrinths.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;entering&quot;&gt;Entering&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I had no experience of labyrinths before encountering one on an afternoon walk. In the corner of a church lawn downtown, a brick-framed-grass path coiled around a thick oak. Not having anything else to do, I considered following it. I didn’t know if it’d feel long or short or if I’d be lost but I asked my body if it was okay with either outcome and it said yes. As a result I spent 15 continuous minutes tracing an undulating circle, while townspeople hustled along the street grid, purposefully traveling from place to place. To be honest, I felt a bit vulnerable, on display. Who was I to flaunt my curvy path among those who only went straight?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These humans will make metaphors out of anything. We also walk around a lot, getting lost. To me this feels like the human condition. Intentionally disorienting paths have popped up on nearly every continent on the planet. There are two main types: unicursal (non-branching) and multicursal (having several branches and usually one solution). Multicursal labyrinths commonly exist for recreational or defensive purposes — think hedge mazes, or the labyrinth where David Bowie hides Sarah’s baby brother in the Jim Henson film Labyrinth (1986). Unicursal labyrinths are more about introspection. I’ve decided to call these ones with unicursal paths “labyrinths” and multicursal paths “mazes”. This contradicts the word labyrinth’s Greek roots — in the myth, King Minos has a beloved yet terribly destructive pet called the Minotaur (anyone else wonder if this was just a euphemism for some royal anger management issues?), so he commissions Daedalus to contain it in an inescapable underground maze. This mostly works fairly well, keeping the people of Crete safe from attack so long as Minos continues to feed it with yearly sacrifices. Historians believe that the tale of the angry mythological beast trapped deep in the earth was invented to explain the earthquakes that regularly plagued Crete for a reason no one understood. Something must have been lost in translation as two millennia past, because these non-branching floor installations I’m talking about today are all called “labyrinths”. So I suppose “labyrinth” still is the word to use.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“If you liked that labyrinth, I have another one for you,” Rhoen said, and our whole house piled into the car the next morning, parking at an empty parking lot next to a scrubby garden. On one side of the garden was a freshly plowed farm and a little marsh; a building that must have been the church was on the other. A sign with a lengthy poem invited all who read it to enter. Crossing a small bridge, I strode straight into the labyrinth. Rhoen followed after spending time addressing the plaques and stone statues. Aneken sat on a bench looking around. They started when they were ready.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;labyrinths__all-saints&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/burlington-all-saints-comm-labyrinth.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A photo taken from the entrance of a walking labyrinth laid out in the middle of a slightly patchy field of grass.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The labyrinth at All Saints Community Labyrinth follows the Chartes pattern.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;labyrinths__all-saints&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;arriving&quot;&gt;Arriving&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I arrive at the center. I am consciously not in a rush. Standing tall, I am learning to focus on me and not on those people in their grid. I greet the oak by walking around it once, giving it enough attention that I hope it won’t feel disrespected. I don’t say hello or goodbye.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lauren Artress started the Labyrinth Movement after a 1991 encounter with Jean Houston (founder of the Human Potential Movement) inspired her to travel to France to walk a labyrinth at the Cathédrale Notre-Dame de Chartres.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; Artress and her companions pushed aside the chairs and walked the eleven course, non-branching Medieval labyrinth built into the nave floor tiles for the first time in 250 years. When she returned home to Grace Cathedral in San Francisco, where she is a priest, she copied the design from Chartres onto a canvas floor tapestry and began to introduce others to the labyrinth, with great success.&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; Given the pervasive but uninformed interest in meditation and “Eastern philosophy” that was popular at the time, it is easy to see why. Labyrinths are simple to make, simple to use, and feel culturally familiar to people from European backgrounds. First working with various personal contacts in the United States and with the International Transpersonal Association in Europe, and eventually creating a non-profit called Veriditas, Artress made it her mission to bring labyrinths to cathedrals, public parks, healthcare facilities, prisons, backyards and spas in many countries.&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; After decades of progress, the organization’s goal has evolved to focus on how to best harness the Labyrinth Experience to facilitate “the transformation of the human spirit”.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I tell myself not to feel underwhelmed at the puddle of gravel that awaits me. I remember when I turned twelve and felt cheated when I realized my birthday did not grant me any more abilities or privileges and, crying, I asked my mother why. I felt even sadder when she told me there wasn’t an answer. Rhoen and then Aneken arrive too and I think about all the highschool kids forced to have quarantine graduations. How important is a threshold to mark the passage of time? I notice that around the large puddle of gray gravel there are smaller rays of red gravel and I put out my arms and start to spin, til red merges with gray and farm merges with road and mirror neurons turn three human bodies into oversized imitations of the year’s last snow flurries swirling in space. For a moment, we’re all here. Eventually we won’t be.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;labyrinths__artress&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/labyrinth-lauren-artress.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A silver haired woman with glasses sits in an arm chair, gesturing toward a circular labyrinth diagram.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Lauren Artress, founder of the Labyrinth Movement, holds a diagram of the floor pattern Chartres Cathedral.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;labyrinths__artress&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;leaving&quot;&gt;Leaving&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now all that’s left is to leave the way you came. Exiting the center, I feel like a pro. The path has already proven itself so there’s no need for a leap of faith. What’s left is just to put one foot in front of the other. All that’s left is just to believe that I can and I will.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the time of their construction, most gothic cathedrals had labyrinths.&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; Their exact function is not precisely known, but clues survive: a description of French clerics using a floor labyrinth in an Easter ceremony; illustrations of pilgrims traversing the labyrinth on their knees; the late 18th century French word for cathedral labyrinths being “chemin de Jerusalem” – literally ‘path to Jerusalem’, which Christians view as the Holy Land.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; Most of these cathedral labyrinths were eventually deemed ‘distracting’ and removed. This makes Chartres an outlier. Despite the labyrinth movement’s adoption by plenty of fringey Christians, mainstream ones dismiss the movement as a New Age-y fad at best, vaguely pagan at worst. And I suppose it is both of these things. Now that I have been initiated, it seems Iabyrinths are everywhere, although not dramatically advertised. And although the four-quadrant unicursal Chartres design was the one that initially inspired Artress, 20th century labyrinths might also opt for the more unified “Classical” design embossed on Cretan coins from 430 BCE,&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; invent their own design, or choose a unicursal maze pattern from Celtic, Hindu or Native American lore. There are no hard and fast rules. Cultural context here is treated as secondary, almost decorative. The primary thing is the walking.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rhoen threatens to break the walls on the way back, so we settle on a run. Bouncing around the labyrinths’ four quadrants I surge ahead of the others, only to fall behind when the path switchbacks in the opposite direction. My lungs burn, I wonder if I’ll trip at the next turn, or the next. I think it’s over sooner than it is, accidentally puncturing the wall of one of the final bends before the neck of the exit. On leaving I circle the exterior, noting commemorative bricks, and reflecting on what just happened. There’s a sundial feature made by a man Rhoen knows from childhood. He exits, and then Aneken, in their own time. We don’t say much of anything. We’ve been on the same path but there were three separate journeys.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;labyrinths__cretan-coins&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/labyrinth-cretan-coin.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Black and white scanned images of two silver coins bearing the Greek letters K N O.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Silver coins from second century Crete embossed with the labyrinth illustrate the Classical 7-course pattern.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;labyrinths__cretan-coins&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Entering</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Glowing Red Memories</title><link href="/2020/03/22/talwst-cant-i-alter.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Glowing Red Memories" /><published>2020-03-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/2020/03/22/talwst-cant-i-alter</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/03/22/talwst-cant-i-alter.html">&lt;p class=&quot;small italic underlined&quot;&gt;
  It's hard to describe how experiencing the collection of work by Curtis Talwst Santiago on view at the Drawing Center made me feel. So I'll settle for describing what I saw in this show entitled &quot;Can't I Alter&quot;...
  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;Post__spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon entering, visitors first encounter a life-sized, beaded suit of armor, nestled in an arch of crumbling plaster supported by iron construction scaffolding. The scenery evokes ancient ruins and the streets of New York, which fits. The work here is the result of a journey that has taken Santiago all over the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;talwst__install-1&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/santiago-cant-i-alter.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Installation view at the Drawing Center in February of 2020.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;talwst__install-1&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;talwst__knight-diorama&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/santiago-artist-as-knight.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Artist as Knight (self portrait). Curtis Talwst Santiago. 2018&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;talwst__knight-diorama&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a stark childhood memory of his first encounter with &lt;em&gt;J’Ouvert&lt;/em&gt;, a Trinidadi festival commemorating the first time formerly enslaved people could celebrate Carnival, and a recent quest into the origins of a 16th century Flemish painting depicting an African Knight of the Order or Santiago, the artist birthed his character ‘Sir Dingolay’. Serving as both the show’s hero and the artist’s alter ego, Sir Dingolay’s presence helps to unite the fruits of the artist’s versatile talents. (In addition to being a thoughtful painter, and an inspired 3-D artist, Santiago is widely acclaimed for his miniature dioramas and has also had a successful career as a Toronto-based dance-rock musician. This might explain his fluency with so many media)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entrance to the show immediately introduces Sir Dingolay in  the form of  his rather festive suit of armor, a life-size garment woven from black, red, white and green beads and wire. Besides evoking the presence of our hero, the wearable sculpture also references the mental ‘armor’ the artist describes needing while traveling the world as a person on color. Nestled inside J’Ouvert Knight, (the only diorama in this collection) our hero appears again in precious miniature. “As with many such objects, this container was likely commissioned as a personal devotional object for a wealthy patron,” the catalogue states. Sir Dingolay also makes an appearance in several of the medium-large in (3 foot square) drawings on canvas that form the bread-and-butter of the exhibit, somewhat ambiguously in &lt;em&gt;Candy Flipping (Boogoo Pouring the Spell in Sir Dingolay’s Ear)&lt;/em&gt; or as a glowing silhouette in &lt;em&gt;The Four of them Made a Promise&lt;/em&gt;. If Sir Dingolay stands in for Curtis Talwst Santiago, are these otherworldly traces based on the artist’s true history?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;talwst__morte-do-cavaliero&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/santiago-a-morte-de-cavaliero.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&quot;A morte do cavaleiro prateado.&quot; Spraypaint, oil, charcoal, pastel, acrylic on canvas. 2018&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;talwst__morte-do-cavaliero&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;talwst__lay-ahead&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/santiago-whatever-lay-ahead.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&quot;Whatever lay ahead he had already accepted&quot;. Spraypaint, oil, charcoal, pastel, acrylic on canvas. 2018.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;talwst__lay-ahead&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;talwst__ancestral-vision&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/santiago-red-face-ancestral-vision-1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&quot;Red Face Ancestral Vision 1.&quot; Spraypaint, oil, charcoal, pastel, acrylic on canvas. 2018&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;talwst__ancestral-vision&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;talwst__promise&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/sanitago-the-four-of-them-made-a-promise.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&quot;The Four of Them Made a Promise.&quot; Spray paint, oil, charcoal, pastel, acrylic on canvas. 2018&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;talwst__promise&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pair of spray-paint drawings on embossed tin tiles She Knight and He Knight, further elaborate on the knight’s mythology. These give the knight some more gravitas; now that he has a companion I start to imagine this avatar as having a life of his own, parallel but separate from the artist. Depicting both male and female knights on equal scale solidly refutes an antiquated belief that the struggle for empowerment men of color face might   require the disempowerment of women of color; in Santiago’s world both the He Knight, She Knight, and the artist himself are magnificent and build one another up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another motif is “red face”. Red clay face paint is a central part of of the J’ouvert festival, and by using reddish spray-paint to turn the faces of various ‘untitled ancestors’ and mythical creatures, the artist creates an interconnected mystique for these beings to which he pays homage. Other times spray-paint just represents a diffuse light, as in A luz (the light), bathing the entire drawing of a robed figure in an archway in a fuzzy glow. In &lt;em&gt;A morte do cavaleiro prateado (The Death of the Silver Knight)&lt;/em&gt;, spray-paint illuminates the face of the J’Ouvert Knight and the nocturnal city in the distance, but neither the plants and trees of the foreground nor the face of the dying companion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Santiago incorporates real light in only one sculpture – a giant nose the size of a motorcycle engine made of golden translucent glass, called &lt;em&gt;Warahoon&lt;/em&gt;. Tucked away behind a replica of a real stone arch that the artist lived near during his time in Bresca, Italy, the nose glows mysteriously from its place on a fluted columnar pedestal. Closer inspection reveals this sculpture to be a bit tongue-in-cheek. “In leiu of the bust to which this nose belongs, the curators have chosen to display only the nose – the other side of the history so often seen in museums,” reads the exhibition catalogue. Iconoclasts seeking to deface statues of deceased individuals (e.g. grave robbers) in Ancient Egypt (Kemet) often broke off statues’ noses, leaving contemporary viewers with a slew of noseless (or worse, poorly restored Caucasian-nosed) statues. With this nose the artist pays a tribute to all the noses lost to history, and all the stories lost with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/398961557&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;music video&lt;/a&gt; plays in the central room, adding a groovy, exciting soundtrack that grounds so many history-defying objects in the honest present. We see the artist finally don the beaded armor and transform into Sir Dingolay. Surrounded by ruins with red pigment brightening his face, he dances the night away to his father’s favorite song (a Calypso tune by the Mighty Sparrow). In this way it all cascades down into the present, all brimming with blood and life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Experiencing this body of work gave me a sense of hope that’s hard to describe. Seeing the artist presenting a heavily realized vision of his personal history — not a history that was written for him by the institution, but a history he sought out and nurtured and imagined into reality — seemed to acknowledge a secret desire I’ve secretly always had for a “better” history. As one of the mutts of the post-colonial society we call the United States, my history always ran contrary to the versions I learned about in school. There are so many blanks, blanks that there will never be adequate records to fill. In “Can’t I Alter”, Santiago seems to argue that with some creativity, a person can take this on. That it’s worth looking for your ancestors, even if their forms come a bit fuzzy. It’s totally possible to create your own mythology. Who’s to say your mythology is less real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;talwst__santiago-with-knight&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/curtis-talwst-santiago-with-armor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The artist poses next to &quot;African Knight I&quot; (wire and beads, on steel armature, 2018).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;talwst__santiago-with-knight&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It's hard to describe how experiencing the collection of work by Curtis Talwst Santiago on view at the Drawing Center made me feel. So I'll settle for describing what I saw in this show entitled &quot;Can't I Alter&quot;...</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PINES</title><link href="/2020/03/11/pines.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PINES" /><published>2020-03-11T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/2020/03/11/pines</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/03/11/pines.html">&lt;p class=&quot;small italic underlined&quot;&gt;
  A few days after the first official cases of COVID-19 hit the streets of New York City, I am embarassed to admit I was not yet cowering in my apartment. Instead I was at Webster Hall, in a claustrophobic crowd of fans waiting to see two members of the 070 collective...
  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;Post__spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first act was 070 Phi, an oddly wise Gen Z-er with glasses and braids, serving up some good quality rap. Then 070 Shake came along to launched us into a new dimension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shake is an engrossing performer, just pure scrappy energy, like a tough being from our collective imagination of the future, come back for a single night to tell us some things about her life. The audience responded with enthusiasm. People screamed loudly on cue, a silver blow-up doll surfed the crod in an inflatable row boat. A lot of 20 year olds from New Jersey bought sugary alcoholic drinks which they spilled liberally while obliviously elbowing me again and again. Doing the math, it was mostly worth the abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;pines__shake-video-still&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://aliciawillett.s3.amazonaws.com/images/blog/070-shake-pines.png&quot; alt=&quot;070 Shake lights a cigarette in front of a group of her friend after a fight. One young man is supported between two others.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The music video for 070 Shake's song &quot;Pines&quot; includes a gnarly fight scene.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;pines__shake-video-still&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toward the end of the set she and the audience all burst out “THE PINES, THE PINES, WHERE WHERE THE SUN DON’T EVER SHINE?” and at that moment the song I’ve been casually humming along to comes into a new focus. Although the mic setup still supplies her signature autotune, now that its live the many layers of production (in which the influence of G.O.O.D. music is dramatic to the point of being overbearing) fall away, exposing more  I get this nerdy “aha” moment where I’m like, whoa its that Lead Belly song!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1993 Nirvana reinterpreted “Where Did You Sleep Last Night” and recorded it as part of their famed MTV Unplugged set.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; It was creepy. When I discovered Nirvana like a decade later, scouring my parents’ house for literally anything to drown out the sounds of middle school, it was creepy, hearing this man shrieking at this young woman, incensed she would lie to him about where she slept last night. It chilled me to hear this hushed-up reality of domestic male rage being admitted in this way. I think I assumed it was about infidelity, and maybe for Cobain it was. Like a lot of Nirvana lyrics it felt like a riddle, a mystery you could flip different ways, and I held tight to it as something I might understand later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually I did an internet search and found out the song was actually a lot older. In 1941 and 1952 Bill Monroe (called the “Father of Bluegrass”)&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; recorded versions of a southern Appalachian folk song sometimes also called “The Longest Train” under the name “In the Pines.”&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; The lyrics in this version describe a train that took three hours to pass and allude to a “little girl” the narrator is mourning without being too specific. In 1944 and 1948 Huddie Ledbetter (stage name: Lead Belly) interpreted the folk song in a more violent an haunting way. Here the narrator seems to be a Black woman mourning the loss of her husband and daughter, decapitated by a moving train and dumped in a pine forest where she cannot find them. Many other versions of this song have been recorded, in music genres from Cajun zydeco to British pop, but the Lead Belly version is the version Kurt Cobain learned from fellow 1990’s Seattle musician Mark Lanegan, and based on the grungy heavy-distortion baseline that opens 070 Shake’s “The Pines”, I’m pretty sure this is the version being referenced here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;pines__leadbelly&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/07/Huddie_Ledbetter_%28Leadbelly%29_taken_by_Alan_Lomax.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A black and white photograph of Huddie Ledbetter wearing a plaid suit and holding an acoustic guitar&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;A photograph of Huddie &quot;Leadbelly&quot; Ledbetter, taken by Alan Lomax in the 1940's.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;pines__leadbelly&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;DoubleImageComponent__col&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent ImageComponent--medium&quot; id=&quot;pines__cobain&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;ImageComponent--image-wrapper flex align-center&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://66.media.tumblr.com/92d772fe3f0c7bd23616093da6e91e04/tumblr_oa83w7bhYt1tyu4qdo1_400.gifv&quot; alt=&quot;Cobain passionately sings the chorus, seated at the mic with his eyes closed.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Kurt Cobain singing &quot;Where Did You Sleep Last Night&quot; with Nirvana at their  historic MTV Unplugged show.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    preloadImage(&quot;pines__cobain&quot;);
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even given this ultimate chameleon of a song, all this is backstory is just a footnote for futurist 070 Shake. “The Pines” is a completely different song. She re-uses the chorus, but the verse is more free-form, more rap. It’s about betrayal, bitterness and probably infidelity, but I don’t get domestic violence vibes here. Instead of a train beheading the villain (in some versions of “In the Pines”, this is how a rapist is killed after his victim escapes into a pine forest), Shake just says “I gotta go/Headed home/To a different timezone.” In the music video, Shake dials up the violence, but drops the romantic themes as she depicts a physical fight that takes place woods between herself and one of her male friends. After the fight which gets ugly to the point of spitting, the video ends with the whole group hanging out in their New Jersey neighborhood like nothing’s wrong. Maybe the fight was just about toughening one another up, or finding an outlet for external rage?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of ways places to put you rage, it’s getting borderline in here. Despite clouds of THC vapor, no one is chill. Shake is grandstanding about loving our neighbors while a guy yells at his date for putting her fingers in his nose. We bounce and cheer to banger after banger, each one it’s own groovy cyborgian musical moment. A beer-soaked dude soaked slams into me and my inner punk launches itself into the moshing abyss. My anxiety and angst rolls off in blissful waves, til I make eye contact with a woman whose looking kinda upset. Next time my feet touch down I allow them to stick in the sugary residue of a spilled drink. Shake hits a crescendo with “Under the Moon” and then plays us out with “Violent Crimes,” the closing track on Kanye’s 2018 album “Ye” that first launched Shake and the 070 collective into the national spotlight. It’s the future, it’s the past, it’s the slow-moving semi-apocalyptic now. Keep slaying NJ. Work on your physical self-awareness if you can.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A few days after the first official cases of COVID-19 hit the streets of New York City, I am embarassed to admit I was not yet cowering in my apartment. Instead I was at Webster Hall, in a claustrophobic crowd of fans waiting to see two members of the 070 collective...</summary></entry></feed>